<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second representation of the hospitaller of St. Thomas Southwark's case in an humble address to the Right Honourable Sir Thomas Pilkinton, lord mayor of the city of London / by J.T.</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63916</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3316</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26335</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09432124</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09432124</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63916)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1318:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second representation of the hospitaller of St. Thomas Southwark's case in an humble address to the Right Honourable Sir Thomas Pilkinton, lord mayor of the city of London / by J.T.</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: John Turner.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hughes, William, b. 1624 or 5.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>St. Thomas's Hospital (London, England)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43079:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Second Repreſentation OF THE HOSPITALLER OF St. <hi>Thomas Southwark's</hi> CASE In an Humble ADDRESS To the Right HONOURABLE Sir <hi>THOMAS PILKINTON,</hi> Lord Mayor OF THE CITY of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, M DC LXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43079:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43079:2"/>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am extremely ſorry it ſo happens through that unhappy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of my Affairs, to which the Importunities of an unjuſt and barbarous Antagoniſt have reduced me, that I muſt be forced to run ſo great an hazard of incurring your <hi>Lordſhip</hi>'s and the Courts diſpleaſure, by this my repeated Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my ſelf againſt the ill practices of ſo bad a Man; becauſe I am ſenſible I cannot do it without calling in queſtion the Validity and Obligation of thoſe ſeveral Orders which have been made by you in his behalf; for if thoſe Orders are as valid and binding upon me, as they are Categorical and poſitive in themſelves, I muſt be guilty in not paying them the Obedience they deſerve of a moſt unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Contempt, for which no Cenſure of offended Juſtice, no Inſtance of your <hi>Lordſhip</hi>'s Indignation and Reſentment could be too great or heavy. But, my <hi>Lord,</hi> I beg your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that tho there have been three ſeveral Orders paſſed for my Ejectment, the firſt only general, and equally reſpecting all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Members and Officers of this Houſe, that were ejected out of it by the late Commiſſion, together with us, that by the ſame Authority were ſubſtituted and appointed in their room; the other two particularly directed againſt me, which as yet I have not been able to perſwade my ſelf, that I am bound in Duty to comply with them; yet this was not done out of any ſtiff, or diſobedient Humor, which is a thing I am as far from as any Man living, being ſo throughly convinced of its pernicious tendency to the diſturbance of Peace and Order amongſt Men. But it was upon this Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, that the whole proceeding ſeemed to me, upon the beſt and moſt impartial Judgment I was capable of making to be ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Firſt, upon a wrong bottom of the Reſtitution of the <hi>Charter,</hi> and Secondly, upon a defective Juriſdiction, which could not legally extend it ſelf ſo far as to the making or paſſing any Order of this nature.</p>
            <p>As to the buſineſs of the <hi>Charter's</hi> being reſtored, that it hath no neceſſary influence upon the Affairs or Officers of our Houſe; That this Regulation might have been made tho the <hi>Charter</hi> had ſtood,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43079:3"/> and that it is not at all affected by its Reſtitution, tho the whole matter had been referred to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and your worthy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, without any Interpoſition of an higher Power, or any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal thereunto; I hope I have demonſtrated beyond all Exception in my former Paper addreſſed to your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Court; and in this I have not ſpoken only my own fence, but that of the beſt Lawyers this Kingdom affords, whoſe Opinions, and the Reaſons of them I have at large tranſcribed from an Authentick Copy, the Original of which, if required, we are ready to produce; and we doubt not in the leaſt but thoſe learned Gentlemen, the juſt Pride and Ornament of the <hi>Long-Robe,</hi> whoſe Opinions ſeldom want the authority and effect of Laws, will firmly abide and ſtand by what they have written, and what they have ſo unanimouſly conſpired and conſented in, led by the force of Truth, which is every where the ſame, without conſulting with or borrowing from each other.</p>
            <p>Now, my <hi>Lord,</hi> with your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> good leave, by this it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears, that neither Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> nor any other of thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that have been reſtored by your Order, had any legal Pretenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their places, by the meer force and virtue of the <hi>Charters</hi> Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and upon ſuppoſition that they had had any, the <hi>Charters</hi> being reſtored would have reſtored them <hi>ipſo facto</hi> together with it ſelf, and they might have compelled us by Law to relinquiſh our Places, without any Order of Court; which could have no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and which pretends to none but from the Reſtitution of the <hi>Charter,</hi> which was, it ſeems, ſufficient of it ſelf to have ejected us without it, and to have put them in poſſeſſion of their ſeveral Places.</p>
            <p>So that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> having no pretention in Law, by vertue of any right annexed to his Perſon by the return of the <hi>Charter;</hi> yet ſuppoſing the Cognizance of that whole Matter to have layn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and the Court of <hi>Aldermen,</hi> as I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it did not, though you might have ejected me, and put him into my Place by vertue of that legally arbitrary and unaccountable Power, that was lodged and veſted in you; yet it would have been highly for the Reputation and Honour of your Court, which I do ſincerely prefer in my own private thoughts before any advantage or intereſt of my own, when all things were equal betwixt Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> and me, as to any ſtrict Property, or legal Right, which neither of us could with any juſtice claim, to have conſidered which of us two had the moſt equitable things to be ſaid in our behalfs; and here
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43079:3"/> tho all other things had been alike between us, yet it is, and hath always been taken as a Maxim, <hi>in equali jure melior eſt conditio poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentis,</hi> that is, If a Controverſie ſhall ariſe or happen between two about a matter of Right, if both of the Pretenders appear to have equal Right, or if neither have any, that is ſtrictly legal; the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations of equity being equal betwixt them, and the one being in poſſeſſion, the other not, the deciſion ought to be in favor of the Poſſeſſor, and your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> knows we have a Proverb to the ſame purpoſe in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, <hi>That Poſſeſſion is eleven Points of the Law,</hi> ſo that according to this Maxim; I being in Poſſeſſion, and all other Circumſtances <hi>ex Hypotheſi</hi> admitted to be equal and alike between us, the Right, if there be any, is mine, and not Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi>'s, becauſe I am in Poſſeſſion, which he is not.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, my <hi>Lord,</hi> I have another advantage, and that a very great one above him, in that I am ſo nearly related to the City, I am my ſelf a Citizen at the firſt remove, and with Submiſſion to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and the Honorable Court, I do affirm that it is your unqueſtionable Duty to favor me before Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> ſuppoſing all other Circumſtances to be but equal between us, and to do otherwiſe falls but little ſhort of a Breach of that Truſt that is repoſed in you, for the good of the City and Citizens, and their Children.</p>
            <p>But things are ſo far from being equal between us, that it appears he never had any Title to this Place, even when he was formerly in Poſſeſſion of it; becauſe for the firſt three years he was not in <hi>Holy Orders</hi> according to the uſage of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> he never had any Epiſcopal Ordination, neither did he ever conform for all that ſpace of time, which in Conſtruction of Law is near one half of a Life, to the Diſcipline and Ceremonies of the Eſtabliſhed Church; and Sir <hi>Simon Degg</hi> ſpeaking of Donatives, as this Chappel is, affirms expreſly upon good authority, beſides what I <note place="margin">Parſon's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, par. 1. o. 13. p. 164.</note> have already repreſented in my former Paper, that the Patron, (who is in this Caſe the King, or Court of <hi>Aldermen,</hi> or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors acting under them) cannot collate a Lay-man, as ſome have thought, but a Spiritual Perſon in <hi>Holy Orders;</hi> and to this it is ſtill further to be added, that this <hi>Hoſpital</hi> being founded by the Piety and Royal Bounty of <hi>Edward</hi> VI. who was in ſome ſence likewiſe the Founder and Eſtabliſher of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> there being but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little difference between his Reformation and ours, as it ſtands improved and Rectified at this day; the deſign of which Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43079:4"/> was on the one hand to aboliſh and extirpate <hi>Popery,</hi> with all its groſs Idolatries and Superſtitions; and on the other, to prevent Schiſm and Diſorder from tearing and rending the Seamleſs Coat of Chriſt, and ſhattering the Church by infinite Separations, it was an affront to the Memory of that Glorious King, to put a Man into his Houſe, and feed him with his Bread, who was as great an Enemy to his Eſtabliſhment, as to <hi>Popery</hi> it ſelf; and thought himſelf obliged in Conſcience, if his Heart and his outward Profeſſion went toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to pull down one Church as well as the other. For in this Caſe, that Will of King <hi>Edward,</hi> which in diſtinction to written, and nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupatory Wills, may be called his <hi>Teſtamentum implicitum,</hi> his Will or Teſtament by implication, or by way of <hi>innuendo,</hi> was manifeſtly and foully violated and broken, to allow a Diſſenting Miniſter in his own Houſe, that would ruine and deſtroy the Reformation he had made, by endeavouring to ſpread and encourage a departure from it, and all this at his proper Coſt and Charge, out of the publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, being certainly as much againſt the true meaning and intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that Prince, and of thoſe good Men under him, who put him upon this Charitable deſign, and were themſelves great Inſtruments in the Reformation; as if a Maſs Prieſt, or Popiſh Monk or Friar had been placed here at the ſame time, for the <hi>Medium</hi> perfectly by being what it is, hath a natural averſion for both of the extremes, and cannot comply with or reconcile it ſelf to either of them, without quitting its Station and forſeiting its Nature; ſo that I cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> could be placed here, without a plain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to the certain, though implicit Will of our Royal Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, neither can I comprehend how the living diſcharge their Truſt, by violating and affronting the Will of the dead, eſpecially when the Laws, which are always ſuppoſed to ſpeak the King's Mind, continue ſtill the ſame as they were before.</p>
            <p>For I grant, that in the late Times the Caſe was otherwiſe, and that it was perhaps better to have a Diſſenting Miniſter in this Houſe, than no Miniſter at all; and that in ſuch caſe ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Preacher ought in juſtice to receive the Wages of the Houſe, though he did not do all the work, that the Founder himſelf, had he been living, would have expected from him, or that the Laws put in Execution would have exacted, and this was much more true of other Officers belonging to this Place, that it was more eligible, ſo they were but honeſt, and fit for their Stations, that Diſſenters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43079:4"/> ſhould be truſted, than that ſo uſeful and ſo great a Charity ſhould be, diſappointed.</p>
            <p>I grant ſtill further, my <hi>Lord,</hi> that even at this time, or at any other before it, when the Laws were moſt rigorouſly put in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, yet no man more than uſually eminent in the Profeſſion of Phyſick, or in the skill of Surgery, or in the dexterity of manual Operation, belonging or appertaining to it, ought to be or to have been diſcarded from his Employment, meerly for his diſſent; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this were to do an injury to the Houſe, and to deprive it of that benefit which it receives by them; but where Men equally or perhaps more skilful and diligent in their Employments may be had that conform to the Eſtabliſhment, as it is ſetled by Law, there it is more agreeable to the Will of our Royal Founder, and to the Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law it ſelf, which in no caſe deſigns to encourage or reward Diſobedience, as ſuch, that Perſons fully qualified by their Conformity to it, ſhould be retained in every publick Service, and receive the Pentions and Salaries of the State.</p>
            <p>And it is ſtill more eminently and univerſally true, that in the Patients themſelves, who are the objects of this Charity, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons intended to be relieved and ſuccoured by it, and for whoſe ſake all Officers and Miniſters are employed and paid; no Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration ſo much as that of Neceſſity and Want, the greater or leſſer need that one or other may have of the aſſiſtance of this Houſe, ought to diſcriminate one Perſon from another, without any regard to a Religious Perſwaſion, which it would be the worſt and moſt inexcuſeable ſort of Perſecution in ſuch a Caſe to conſider.</p>
            <p>But none of all this was Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Caſe, the Law allowing no Preacher but a Conformiſt, and much leſs rewarding him for ſuch his Service out of the publick Revenue, and without having recourſe to the Implicit will of our Royal Patron and Founder King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. (though that be ſo manifeſt, by Indications that cannot deceive, that there can be no longer doubt of the matter) by the plain, explicit and poſitive Inſtitution of his Royal <hi>Charter,</hi> It is ordained among other things, that he ſhall be a Prieſt or a Perſon qualified, not only to Preach or Pray, but alſo to adminiſter the Sacrament upon occaſion, and this is an Office which none but a Prieſt rightly qualified and ordained according to the Conſtitution of the <hi>Church of England</hi> can legally perform; ſo that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> was unqualified, not only according to the Laws of this Land,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43079:5"/> and the implicit Will, but according to the expreſs and poſitive Inſtitution of that bleſſed King, who had certainly the greateſt and moſt unqueſtionable Right, to impoſe what lawful terms he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon his Servants, and they are all lawful Conditions, when we ſpeak in a civil and political Sence, that are Conditions according to Law; for I do not enter into the merits of the Cauſe betwixt the Diſſenters and us.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> I hope, will pardon me, that I ſuggeſt ſo many things in this my ſecond Paper, that have been already repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my firſt; you may perceive Sir, that I do it in a ſome what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Method from what I did before, leaving out thoſe Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in this ſhort review, which however true and certain in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, afforded but too much occaſion for Offence, and ſtarting new matter for Remark and Obſervation as I go along; it being my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to ſet all things as near as I can in a ſomewhat clearer light, and to contract the whole into a ſhorter compaſs, that ſo your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> may conſider it with the leſſer trouble, and at a nearer view, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſo much diſturbance to the great Affairs that are the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe buſie hours, of which the Publick neither muſt nor will be defrauded.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> all that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> hath to urge in his own defence, when he is charged with Non-conformity for three years together, while as a Miniſter he received the Wages of this Houſe, is this, he doth not deny, nay, not ſo much as extenuate or excuſe the thing, but all is well, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> that ends well; he was in Orders for a twelve Month or thereabouts, before he left the Place; and this he thinks was a Confirmation without a new Choice, and that his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in the Houſe for ſo long after his aforeſaid Ordination, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to as much as if after Reſignation he had been formally elected by a Majority of thoſe that had a Right to do it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what I have ſaid already upon this occaſion, which, I hope, your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> in Juſtice to me, will, at your leiſure conſider, Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> either never knew or is not willing to remember, that it is a Maxim in the Civil Law, which in this is founded on the higheſt Reaſon; <hi>Quod ab initio non valet tractu temporis non convaleſcit:</hi> That title which is defective and faulty in its beginning, cannot be ſtrengthened by continuance, uſance, or by length of Time; and the learned Lawyer whom I have above-cited in the Caſe of Donatives, alledging this very Reaſon, puts this Caſe in the buſineſs of Plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43079:5"/> which I have a little enquired into for Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi>'s <note place="margin">Part 1. c. 4. p. 28.</note> ſake. <hi>If the eldeſt Son of a Duke, Marqueſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>retain Chaplains in the life-time of his Father, who after dyes, and the Honour deſcends upon ſuch Son, yet this retainer will not qualifie his Chaplains to have Pluralities within the Statute,</hi> (by which a Duke, Marqueſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may qualifie their Chaplains to hold Plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities at the ſame time,) <hi>becauſe at the time of the retainer he was not capable to qualifie them, Et quod ab initio non valet tractu tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris non convaleſcit.</hi> From whence the Application is eaſie to our preſent Caſe; for if a Clerk being Chaplain to the Son of a Duke or Marqueſs, who as ſuch cannot qualifie his Chaplain for a Plurality, ſhall yet notwithſtanding under this pretence poſſeſs and occupy two Livings at the ſame time, and this without controll till the death of his Patrons Father, when he, becoming Duke or Marqueſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, hath a legal Title to qualifie his Chaplain; and the ſaid Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain by his being ſuch, is in a legal capacity of being qualified by him; but yet notwithſtanding this, he ſhall not hold both of thoſe Spiritual Preferments together, by virtue of his former retainer: but upon Information exhibited againſt him, he ſhall be obliged to ſurrender the firſt of his Preferments, which became void in Law at the very moment of his being fully and peaceably poſſeſt of the latter, and hath continued in Law to be void ever ſince that time: Then the Caſe is clear in Oppoſition to Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> that his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion being illegal, and his Election void in Law at the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant when he was choſen, though he were afterwards in a Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city to be legally elected, yet without an actual Reſignation on his part, and an actual Re-election on the part of thoſe that choſe him, or of others fitly qualified to appoint and chuſe him; no connivance or ſufferance was ſufficient for his purpoſe in this Caſe, any more than in the other; for the Rule is equally applicable to both Caſes; <hi>quod ab initio non valet, tractu temporis non convaleſcit;</hi> That title which is vitious and faulty in the beginning, cannot be mended after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by length of Time, which is not to be underſtood in Prejudice to Preſcription, which is a legal Title; but of thoſe leſſer periods of time that are confined within the narrow compaſs of a few years, or wherein one Man's Life or Poſſeſſion is concerned.</p>
            <p>If the Clerk in the firſt Caſe reſigning his Living, ſhall afterwards obtain a new Preſentation to it from the Patron, which in this Caſe muſt generally be the Biſhop or the King, the Living being ſuppoſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43079:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> to be lapſed for want of a legal Incumbent; he may then by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the Duke or Marqueſs or other qualifying Perſonage that retains him, obtain a legal qualification for the re-enjoyment of it, together with his other Preferment, but not elſe: And by the ſame reaſon Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> having actually reſigned, and being actually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſen, might have pretended ſomething of a Title to his laſt years Poſſeſſion of this Place; but his firſt choice being void, and no new choice being made, no connivance or ſufferance can avail him any thing in this affair, any more than it would in the other; ſo that it is plain he never had any Title, and if to this we add his groſs and foul neglect in the Execution of his pretended Charge, from which he can never purge and vindicate himſelf. I preſume it will be granted by all Men, that a weaker Cauſe never had the Honor of ſo great a Patronage, as that of your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> and thoſe other Gentlemen, that through miſinformation in the true State of Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Caſe, have been ſo unfortunately Charitable to believe, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly kind as to protect him.</p>
            <p>This is the third Conſideration, by which it may appear not only that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> hath no ſuch legal Right as he pretends to, but that in Equity I have much the advantage of him, upon Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition that my firſt appointment and miſſion to this Place was le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, (which his was not) of which I ſhall ſay more hereafter; and I think two Talleys or Indentures cannot ſtrike more exactly than the Caſe of Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> doth with that other above mentioned, which, it ſeems, is a ruled Caſe, and therefore concludes the more ſtrongly againſt his Pretences; let him waſh his Hands of it as he can.</p>
            <p>A fourth Conſideration in Equity, is this, That Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after his Ejection out of this Place, had another beſtowed upon him of double the value; and a Freehold inſtead of an arbitrary Dependance; for which no Man would give a years Purchaſe if it were to be ſold, conſidering how tickliſh and uncertain words <hi>duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te beneplacito</hi> are uſually found to be; whereas a Freehold in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acceptation is, for one Life, worth ſeven; and the intrinſick Value is the ſame in Spiritual Preferments, though they are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bought or ſold: So that admitting Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Living to be double the value of his late Preferment here, which is the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt account it can be computed at; the advantage he hath gotten by his remove from this to that, is in the proportion of fourteen to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43079:6"/> one; an exchange for which I think he ought to be thankful to the kind Providence that ejected him from hence, without endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to reinſtate himſelf againſt ſo many and great reaſons as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt him, and which he can anſwer with nothing but an hard forehead, which is proof againſt Conviction, and is placed above the baſhful Region where modeſty and bluſhes dwell; nay, ſuppoſe that placing a Curate in his Country-Living, for I take it for granted your Lordſhip will not endure a Non-reſident in this Place, he can after all ſecure twenty Pound <hi>per annum de claro</hi> to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yet this according to our former Computation, is an advantage no greater than one in <hi>Forty Two;</hi> and what ſort of Creature, or rather Monſter of Covetouſneſs and Envy muſt this Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> be, who will eject me out of two thirds to gain one to himſelf, and that one but the two and fortieth part in common Eſtimation, of what I was the contingent occaſion of his getting, by being ſubſtituted in his room in this Houſe?</p>
            <p>His Living, <hi>my Lord,</hi> as I have been informed is at a place called <hi>Little Stoughton</hi> in the County of <hi>Bedford,</hi> and he lets it at this time for an hundred and ten pounds a year, and by that its true value ſhould be about ſevenſcore, that is, about twenty or thirty pound <hi>per annum</hi> more then his Tenant pays; for no Man will take the trouble of farming it upon him, without a proſpect of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage amounting to thus much at leaſt; now being reſident up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place, he may if he pleaſeth take his Tithes as they ariſe in kind, without injury or ſo much as inconvenience to any, for the Farmer will be ſure to make all the advantage, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf might lawfully have done; but if he be non-reſident, as he muſt be in this caſe, if your Lordſhip and the Court perſiſt in your reſolution of beſtowing the Hoſpital upon him, and he in his of accepting what you offer, it will then be his beſt way to ſet the profits of his Living to Farm, but then nothing is more clear than that at the foot of the account he will not get one farthing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the bargain, and will you, my Lord, do me ſo great an injury who am a Citizens Son, for the ſake of an Alien, a Foreiner, and an ill Man, who can get nothing by it, but the gratification of a groundleſs malice and prejudice againſt me, a paſſion which it ill becomes the honour and juſtice of your Court, to countenance and encourage in any Man whatſoever, and much more in one of Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Character and profeſſion. Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> indeed is pleaſed to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43079:7"/> ſay betwixt jeſt and earneſt; for it looks like a jeſt, though it be ſpoken ſeriouſly, that this Living was not given him in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Hoſpital which he loſt, but for ſome other reaſon, God knows what, but I am ſo bold to affirm that I have proved plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the nature of the gift it ſelf, compared with the ſmall Preferment he was deprived of, that it was for this very reaſon, and that it could be for no other. And beſides this, I have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to the ſacred teſtimony of a right noble and right Reverend Prelate of our Church, together with ſeveral other eminent and learned Perſons of the greateſt repute and Authority belonging to it, before whom Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> dare not ſhew his hypocritical and diſhoneſt face, out of a ſenſe of the ingratitude and baſeneſs of this pretence, which is ſo great a diminution to the kindneſs and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity they ſhewed him at that time, and includes moreover an arrogant and proud aſſuming to himſelf, as if his merit and not their compaſſion had extorted and ſnatcht that generous benefaction from them.</p>
            <p>I never heard any thing urged to palliate ſo groſs and palpable a falſhood, but that the conſideration was not given him by the ſame Perſons that ejected him from hence, and therefore they conclude and argue like themſelves, who underſtand neither Premiſſes nor Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as they ought to do, that one was not given him in lieu of the other: but thoſe Gentlemen know beſt upon what motive they did it, and to them I make my humble, but yet confident Appeal, which Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> with all his impudence dare not do, and I do really reſent the injury, and affront which is done to the City and the Court of Aldermen by ſuch a barefac'd Lye, inſinuated with all the ſeeming ſincerity and addreſs, which is only natural to truth, and very ill becomes that Falſhood and diſguiſe, which incapable of a modeſt and juſt aſſeveration, needs a meretricious and feigned one to ſupport it. One worthy Member of the honourable Court was pleaſed to tell me in the Court it ſelf, that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Living was not given him in conſideration of his loſs, to which with all humility I reply'd, That though I had ſeveral other things to urge againſt him, yet I was very willing to put the Iſſue of the whole matter upon this ſingle Point, and I continue ſtill firmly in the ſame reſolution, notwithſtanding he cannot anſwer or vindicate himſelf from any one thing that I have urged againſt him, and if there were nothing elſe but this to be conſidered, by this you may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43079:7"/> ſee my Lord, what manner of Man it is that pretends and would be thought to fly to you for Refuge; but hath indeed no other but only in ſhams and evaſions: I ſhall wonder very much, upon ſo fair a detection, if your Lordſhip and the Court ſhall patronize him any longer, who hath abuſed and impoſed upon the Charity and goodneſs of the Bench you ſit on, at ſo unmannerly and ſo vile a rate. I refer my ſelf very willingly to your Honor and Judgment, whether that Man ought to be entruſted with the Conſciences of others, who diſcovers ſo plainly that he hath none of his own? who pimps and proſtitutes his Word and Soul upon no other conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able advantage, but only the gratification of an unchriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, very diſagreeable to a Man of his Cloth and Function, and the fruitleſs purgation of an inexhauſtible Spleen, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news it ſelf by waſting, like the Widows Cruize, and knows nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end nor meaſure? nay, I cannot chuſe but ſmile within my ſelf, at ſuch an extremely pleaſant and ſurpriſing Notion, that nothing could be given him in lieu of what he had loſt; unleſs it had been given him by the ſame hands that deprived him of his ill-gotten and ill-deſerved Poſſeſſion in this Houſe; which yet it is manifeſt they could not do without a diſowning of their own Act, and an implicit acknowledgment that they had done him wrong; whereas it is but too apparent, with ſhame for Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> I ſpeak it, becauſe he ſeems to have none left for himſelf, that they proceeded but upon too juſt and juſtifiable grounds.</p>
            <p>In the fifth place, let me intreat your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> to conſider, that this intended Preferment or Reſtitution of Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> added to the Country Living already in his Poſſeſſion, makes him in Conſcience a Pluraliſt, whatever he be in Law: and this with reſpect to him is <hi>argumentum ad hominem;</hi> It is a Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon of his own making, drawn againſt himſelf; he being a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and printed Enemy to Pluralities and Non reſidence, and if he hath either Shame, Conſcience or Honeſty left about him, he muſt either relinquiſh one of theſe two Places, or give ſome publick Reaſons in defence of a Practice, which he formerly exploded, that we may be ſatisfied upon what Grounds this ſtrange and avowed Alteration of his Opinion depends. It is not only a Plurality in Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and in Conſcience, but it is likewiſe a Plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity <note place="margin">So alſo in Attic. Regin. Eliz. 1584. &amp; 1597. in the Canons of 1571. the difference is but twenty ſix Miles.</note> out of diſtance, thirty Miles being the fartheſt that the Canon of K. <hi>James</hi> I. in that behalf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, <hi>Can.</hi> 41. whereas theſe two Places are forty
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43079:8"/> Miles apart, that is, ten Miles more than the <hi>Canon</hi> permits to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons qualified by Law for two Benefices with cure of Souls, which I conceive Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> is not; and the Reaſon againſt Pluralities, which is the very ſame upon which our Law proceeds, is alledged by Sir <hi>Simon Degg</hi> out of an ancient Councel in theſe words, <hi>Res ipſa loquitur plura Beneficia, potiſſimum quibus cura</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Parſon's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor. part 1. p. 18.</note> 
               <hi>animarum ſubmiſſa eſt, non ſine gravi Eccleſiarum dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ab uno obtineri; cum unus in pluribus Eccleſiis rite officia perſolve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, aut rebus earum neceſſariam curam impendere nequeat;</hi> That is, the thing ſpeaks very plainly for it ſelf; that two Benefices, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with cure of Souls, cannot be enjoyed or occupied by one Perſon without great damage and detriment to the Church, becauſe one and the ſame Perſon cannot attend ſo particularly as he ought to do in ſeveral Churches, to the neceſſary and indiſpenſeable Duties that are incumbent upon him, and if this cannot well be done at thirty Miles diſtance, which is the utmoſt diſtance that our Law allows, it can much leſs at forty, which is Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi>'s Caſe; and though the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> do not require Inſtitution from the Biſhop, which is the thing that makes a ſtrict and legal Plurality; yet the Conſcience of the Caſe does perhaps ſit more cloſely upon him, than it would do in a legal Benefice at the ſame diſtance, becauſe of the number of ſick that are always in this Place, and the Perſonal attendance that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired upon them: to ſay nothing of the lewd lives of ſo many of the Patients before their admiſſion into this Houſe for cure: So that tho the letter of the Statute do not preſs him, yet the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and the Reaſon of it, which to every honeſt Man ought to be more ſacred and obligatory than the other, can never be ſhaken off by any Man that hath a Conſcience, and much leſs by him that hath written ſo expreſly, not to ſay ſo paſſionately againſt this practice in others; therefore he can do no leſs in common Honeſty and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, before he accepts this kindneſs from your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Court, than ſatisfie the World what Reaſons have induced him to alter his Opinion, for without this, I am ſure, he can never juſtifie ſo foul a Practice. And, my <hi>Lord,</hi> I beg of your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that it hath been reſolved by the Judges, as my <hi>Parſon's Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor</hi> informs me, That the King himſelf cannot diſpenſe with this Statute againſt Pluralities, where the Statute it ſelf <note place="margin">Ib. p. 29.</note> does not diſpenſe with them, of which there are ſeveral inſtances to be met with in it, though in ſome Particulars, and to ſome Perſons,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43079:8"/> and in ſome certain Circumſtances, the Lawyers have agreed, whether right or wrong is none of my buſineſs to determine, that the King may diſpence; and how then can your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Court, by giving Mr, <hi>Hughes</hi> the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> at this time, diſpence with the Reaſon and Conſcience of a Statute, when the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, becauſe of the apparent Equity upon which it is founded, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſpence ſo much as with the letter of it? Though the firſt be much more Sacred than the latter, for the Law, as meerly written, is poſitive and changeable, but as founded upon Reaſons of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and unchangeable good; it is eſſential, unalterable, and eternal.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, my Lord, are ſo very plain and ſtrong upon Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> and he begins as thick and impenetrable as his Skull is (as hard almoſt as his heart and conſcience themſelves) to be ſo ſenſible of it, that I have been well inform'd by thoſe that have it from his Confidents and Friends, that he now gives it out as a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret in truſt, to be whiſpered abroad, as there ſhall be a fit occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; that he deſigns not to hold both of theſe Places together, but that upon his reſtitution to this houſe, he will immediately relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh it again and leave the Governours to a new choice, and if they were left to it, I ſhould be very ſorry it ſhould appear I had behaved my ſelf ſo, as that I ſhould not deſerve the favour of their Votes againſt any other Pretender, however the Court of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, without giving me a fair and equal hearing, and without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the reaſons upon which they did it, have been pleaſed to carry it againſt me.</p>
            <p>This account given by Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> and his Friends of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition out of the Land of <hi>Bedford,</hi> into that of <hi>Middleſex</hi> and <hi>Surrey,</hi> hath at firſt ſight a very malicious and ſpiteful aſpect upon me, and I doubt not after all, but it is more than a Copy of his countenance, it ſhews the true face and feature of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, though he was not willing to venture it abroad without a Maſque to conceal it from every common view, and make it walk <hi>incognito</hi> about the ſtreets under the diſguiſe of better and more ſpecious Names. The reaſon given out by him, as I have really been told and am ready to produce a much honeſter Man than ever Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> was or will be for my witneſs, is, that he came out of tenderneſs to the poor and ſick of this Houſe, about whom he hath been ſtrangely ſollicitous for theſe five years paſt, though it is well known they were never more ſlende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>garded, than
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43079:9"/> when he himſelf was here, and it muſt be confeſſed, my Lord, to be very frank and generous in him, and without any mixture of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt or ſelf-deſign, that he is ſo very watchful and jealous for the Souls of other People, with which he hath not ſo immediately to do, and for which he is to give no account, when he is at the ſame time ſo laviſh of his own, as if it were good for nothing but to be loſt and thrown away. He ſaith, I am unfit for my Employment; and I confeſs it; For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> but if all Men that are unworthy of their Employments muſt be turned out of what they legally enjoy, becauſe there may be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers upon the compariſon more worthy, what will become of Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> himſelf? Or would it not have been better for him to have ſtaid, as he might have done quietly at home, than to have come ſo far to draw up an invidious impeachment againſt me, which reflects back again from whence it came, with much more ſeverity and juſtice upon himſelf? For if the account I have given your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and the Court in my former Paper be true, and I will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable for the truth of it, however mean and unworthy I may be in my ſelf, yet upon a fair hearing of the matter between both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, upon a true repreſentation of the management of this Houſe, ſo far as the ſpiritual Province is concerned, in Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his time and mine, I doubt not, nay, I am very well aſſured, though he were to pack and pick a Pannel of his own Friends to try the Iſſue betwixt us, that the Verdict would and muſt be very much to my advantage, and Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> may ſee, if he will caſt his Eye that way, That I am no ſuch lazy, unperforming Creature as he would repreſent me, by this my double Apology for my ſelf, and defence of my moſt juſt and righteous Cauſe, againſt the injuſtice and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity of his, which he will never be able to anſwer while he lives, and by not anſwering, confeſſeth that he hath done me wrong, and that he puts your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Honourable Bench upon doing thoſe things in his favour, by the miſt which he hath caſt before the Truth of the matter, which he himſelf cannot juſtifie to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or you.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> I am very ſenſible that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> values himſelf ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much upon his Preaching, and that it is ſome defect of mine in this part of my Employment, which is the ground and root of that unfitneſs, for which he would eject me, and will moſt certainly if ever he be advanced, to the formidable ſtile and dignity of a tryer; but in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43079:9"/> the mean time, my Lord, let us play a Prize of Preaching if you pleaſe upon a Text and Subject whch your Lordſhip ſhall aſſign, and if I do not paſs upon the compariſon for a pretty midling Divine, and Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> for the ſame Tub-preacher that ever he was, then he ſhall eject me, and do what elſe he pleaſeth to gratifie this Chriſtian zeal of his, though he can get nothing but infamy by the bargain.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I do not pretend to great things, but plain Sermons among plain People are beſt, and ſeveral ſuch I have preached; if Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> after a long courſe of Hypocriſie and time, have arrived to a greater Perfection than ſimple Men pretend to in the two great Accompliſhments of Cant and Grimace, I can as little help and do as little envy his Attainments, as I am Maſter of them: but true Edification, if I take it right, is onely to be had from ſober ſenſe, from plain and inſtructive Diſcourſes, otherwiſe Men may edifie, that is, they may without queſtion work themſelves into a ſerious and devout temper, by worſhipping of Images and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, by ſprinkling with holy Water, or whipping with a Cat of Nine-Tails, and by many other extravagancies of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> but a Man is not edified every time he thinks or vainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits he is, upon grounds of meer Fanſie and Imagination; but when he underſtands his Duty and the reaſons of it, and upon this is excited to a Manly Repentance, and to a wiſe reſolution of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment; but after all the good that is attained by one Man's affected Tone, or by anothers Geſture and Phraſe, though it may poſſibly have an wholeſom influence upon the lives and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſome men, yet in it ſelf it is an edg-tool dangerous to meddle with, it is the method by which all religious madneſs and Enthuſiaſm proceeds, and he that affixes Edification or Salvation to any ſuch Whimſies as theſe, for in very truth and reality they are no better, after all his bitter Invectives againſt Popery, is him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf nothing elſe but a worſhipper of Idols.</p>
            <p>It is very ſtrange to me how Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> ſhould bring ſo much Conſcience with him out of the Countrey when he carried ſo little with him thither: one great reaſon of his ejectment from hence, and by conſequence of what followed after it, his going into the Countrey, was, becauſe of his groſs neglect in the diſcharge of his Duty, and now he would be thought to return becauſe of mine; and how very likely it is that the neglect of my Duty, if any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43079:10"/> ſuch there were, ſhould go ſo near his Heart, when for four years together, he never had any ſence of his own; I leave it to your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and to all Mankind to determine.</p>
            <p>How little ſence of Religion, and even of common Honeſty, Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> carried down with him to his Country Living, for an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to the Flock committed to his care, may be geſſed from his uſage of the Reverend Incumbent to whom he ſucceeded in it, whom he had the Grace to Perſecute; and it is thought would have proſecuted for dilapidations, notwithſtanding he reſigned a conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able time, and quitted all Profits before he need to have done it, to Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his incomparably greater benefit and advantage; for the ſum he demanded was no more than fifteen Pounds; though this is the more remarkable by what hath hapned ſince, that this was the very ſame Sum which the other day he had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to demand of mine, it being my laſt Quarters Salary for this Houſe, which I earned every penny without any aſſiſtance of his. And our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf tells us, applying what he ſaith to our very Function and Buſineſs, <hi>That the Labourer is worthy of his hire.</hi> He did not ſo much as put in his claim to my Place till two thirds or more of the Quarter were expired, and he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <note n="a" place="margin">My Order was dated, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 13. 1683. that is ſix weeks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day, tho I did not enter upon the Place ſo ſoon.</note>, that upon his own Reſignation, which was ſomewhat above a Fortnight before the Quarter day, he had the whole Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of that Quarter allowed him, though about fifty Shillings of it in ſtrictneſs would have been mine; and now he would have all my Salary for doing nothing, which was ſo far from the uſage that I have offered others, that upon the late Incumbent of St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s Death, I allowed the whole Salary of the next Quarter to the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, as I thought in cuſtom and civility I ought to do, he dying ſomewhat after Quarter day, though I took care of that whole Quarter my ſelf, and paid the Curate out of my own Pocket.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant he pretends an Order of Court, and for ought I know he doth but pretend it, for the Original I never ſaw, nor any Copy well atteſted, for his excuſe in this matter; but I am ſo well ſatisfied of the Honour of that Illuſtrious Body, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they have been very much impoſed upon by falſe Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, and through multitiplicity of Buſineſs at this time, have not had the leiſure to enter into the merits of ſo inconſiderable a Cauſe as this is; I ſay, I am ſo well ſatisfied, that I am ſure they would not have paſſed an Order of this nature, but only for theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43079:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> two Reaſons: Firſt, That they thought upon the miſtaken Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions that had been made to them; that the undoubted Right was in Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> and therefore they gave this Order in <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem,</hi> that ſo his Right might take place, and I be compelled, or at leaſt very ſtrongly enclined to pay an Obedience to it, out of a proſpect of advantage on the one hand, or elſe of puniſhment for my Contempt on the other, not that they intended this Order ſhould ever be executed in its literal ſtrictneſs and ſeverity; but it was by way of Experiment or by way of <hi>valeat quantum valere poteſt,</hi> to try what I would do upon the Advertiſement I received of it; and indeed I had ſubmitted to it, and I ſhould ſtill be very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to do the ſame, but only for theſe two Conſiderations, firſt, That by ſo doing I ſhould ſeem to allow that the Authority that made this Order, for the Quarters ſalary becoming due at the Feaſt of the <hi>Annunciation</hi> laſt paſt, which I had earned with my Labours in this Houſe, might with equal Reaſon make another to entitle him to all the mean Profits for theſe five years together, which I muſt either obey or go to Priſon for not doing it, if ſuch an Order had been good in Law, which tho I did not believe that ever it would be done, yet not to diſpute this Order, was in effect to acknowledge the Legality of that, and to call my ſelf by thoſe names which Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> only deſerves, for having unjuſtly received the Wages of this Houſe for ſo many years together, neither would it be pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or adviſeable in any Man in the World, out of a too profuſe reſpect and deference to any limited Authority whatſoever, to run the hazard of the minuteſt poſſibility of ſuch a fatal Conſequence as this.</p>
            <p>That your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Court did not intend to uſe all that extremity of Rigour with me, which ſuch an Order at firſt view might ſeem to threaten me with, appears very plain and evident to me by this, that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> was denied his Money when he came for it; and Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> by claiming it, ſo contrary to Senſe and Juſtice, hath pronounced a greater Satyr againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf than it is poſſible for Wit and Indignation in confederacy toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to write or invent againſt him; and your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> I hope, will be pleaſed for the future, having made this Experiment of Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> as well as me, not to hearken too much to his clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Pretences of a legal Claim, when you ſee ſo plainly, that all is Fiſh with him that comes to Net; and that his legal Claims have no other bound or meaſure, than the Arbitrary Dependences of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43079:11"/> 
               <hi>French</hi> King, that is, every thing is his, and legally too by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Law that runs through all his deſigns, and equally juſtifies every thing he does, which he can graſp or come at, at the inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a will, that admits no practical Conſcience for its guide, and by the help of all the little Power he is Maſter of, and all the crafty, circumventing Arts he can uſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing, beſides the uncertainty of the Order it ſelf, which does not yet appear to me to be authentick, why I neither did nor could pay it that ſubmiſſion, which otherwiſe no Man ſhould have done more chearfully than my ſelf, was that it ſeemed to me to be too hard meaſure while I am under the apprehenſion that my Poſſeſſion is legal, for me to ſubmit to an Order, which with all humble Duty and ſubmiſſion I muſt affirm, I cannot believe to be ſo, which would be for me to juſtifie by my own act of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and in a manner to acknowledg the legality of a proceeding againſt my Conſcience and my Intereſt together, which is too great an hardſhip even for Slaves and Vaſſals to endure; but if the Law will eject me, <hi>currat lex,</hi> I deſire no other favour than what the Law will afford me; but in all other things I am and ſhall always be ready to pay my lawful Superiours all poſſible obedience, ſo far as is conſiſtent with my honeſt Intereſt, in conjunction with my unqueſtionable Duty; For, my Lord, I have a Family to provide for beſides my ſelf, and it is therefore my duty to aſſert any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Intereſt that may tend to our common ſupport, but in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe where my Duty and my preſent advantage cut upon and interfere with one another, I hope I ſhall always have the grace to look to the peace of my Conſcience, the honour of my Profeſſion, the reputation of my Name among good Men, and ſo to conſider my whole intereſt together, which my Antagoniſt does not ſeem to do, as not to forfeit my Title to a bleſſed immortality, and my proſpect of ſeeing the face of God with comfort, for the ſake of any periſhing and momentany advantage.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip, when I began this my humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation and Addreſs, which I did not intend to ſpin out to ſo great a length, in the midſt of ſo great importunities of publick buſineſs, as every moment ſollicit and invite your care; I mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned theſe two conſiderations as the reaſons, why I did not pay that deference to the Orders of the Honourable Court for my Eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which was expected from me; The firſt, That the ſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43079:11"/> proceeded upon a wrong bottom of the reſtitution of the Charter; And ſecondly, upon a defective Juriſdiction, which could not legally extend it ſelf ſo far, as to the making or paſſing any Order of this nature.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe, after all that hath been ſaid upon it, is, I preſume, ſo clear, if there be any ſuch thing as Law or Reaſon in the World, that, I hope, your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Court will be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied as to that point, that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> hath no legal Right naturally accruing to and devolving upon him by this new and happy ſettlement of Affairs upon their ancient Baſis and Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo that ſo far as your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Court of <hi>Aldermens</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction is concerned, if there were no Superiour Authority, no higher Appeal, it is a matter of Equity that lies before you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> and my ſelf, whether he ſhould be reſtored or I continued in the Poſſeſſion I have; and I am willing to refer my ſelf after a due Reflection upon what I have here humbly repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> to Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> himſelf, who ſhall be Judge and Party in his own Cauſe, whether all the equitable Pretenſions are not mine, or whether it be poſſible in point of Equity, which is the Law of Conſcience, the Light of Nature, the bleſs'd reſult of Goodneſs and Juſtice together, for any Cauſe to have more to be ſaid in its defence than mine hath, or more to be ſaid againſt it than his.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond point of defective Juriſdiction, I muſt again take the Liberty, and I hope I ſhall do it without Offence to your Lordſhip, any juſt and unprovoked Occaſion of which I am natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally very tender of giving, to aſſert the Kings Title in oppoſition to that of any ſubordinate Authority acting under it, and to ſay that what the ſupreme Power hath lawfully eſtabliſhed, that no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior can diſanull, unleſs upon emergent Neceſſity, or apparent Reaſon, without unhinging of Government, and inverting the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the Order of things. I grant indeed though the firſt Orders proceeded upon the Suppoſition of the Reſtitution of the Charter, (for the laſt of the three hath made no mention of it) which ſaid ſuppoſition was plainly miſtaken and ungrounded; yet if the ſole, entire and abſolute Diſpoſal of this matter had layn properly before you, without any further Appeal, which, (when the King hath already determined) it doth not; that in ſuch Caſe the miſtaken ground would not have evacuated the Order that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43079:12"/> was built upon it, unleſs you ſhould pleaſe to recall it, or to let it fall of it ſelf, becauſe abſolute Power is under no Obligation to aſſign a Reaſon; it may act without giving a Reaſon, as well as with it, and a bad Reaſon can never diſanull that Order, merely becauſe it cannot juſtifie it ſelf, whoſe true Authority conſiſts in the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Promulgation of the Will of the ordaining Power, which Will if it continues, the Order is valid to all Intents and Purpoſes, tho the Reaſon, upon which it is or may be built, be never ſo weak and infirm: But in this Caſe where the will of the Ordainer doth not extend ſo far, the Order is invalid by defect of Juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Simon Degg,</hi> who is my Counſel, tells me, that the King may give a Licence to a Subject to erect, or found <note place="margin">P. C. part. 1. c. 13. p. 164.</note> a Church or Chappel donative, and exempt it from the Ordinaries Viſitation; and the Patron may in ſuch Caſe, viſit by his own Commiſſioners: And ſhall not the King, My Lord, be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to do that legally by his own immediate Power, that is, to viſit, by his own Commiſſioners, in his own Houſe and Chappel, which, at the ſame time, he may empower and priviledge any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Patron to do in his or her proper Gift, without Remedy or Appeal? And as to the Union of the two places, the ſame Author tells us, that the Canoniſts allow even of Pluralities in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 18. ib.</note> ſix Caſes, of which one is the ſmalneſs of each Living by it ſelf, and another where two Churches are united (he muſt mean either by Contiguity or Authority, one of which is a natural, the other a legal Union) or depend the one upon another. And in another Place he ſaith, the uniting of Churches ought <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 170. ib.</note> to be, <hi>causâ utilitatis five neceſſitatis,</hi> as Vicinity, Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Inhabitants, Smalneſs of the Livings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Perſons that muſt concur to the Union, are the King, the Ordinary, and the Patron, and if any of the Places be full, the Conſent <note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 169. ib.</note> of the Incumbent likewiſe is neceſſary to it; of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to my own advantage, I ſuppoſe no body will make a Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eſpecially when I am pleading for the Continuance of it, and the King, the Ordinary and Patron, being in this Caſe all of them the ſame, it is impoſſible there ſhould be a ſtronger Conſent, or by conſequence a firmer and more inſeparable Union, ſo far as my Perſon is concerned, (for it extends no farther) than this is.</p>
            <p>It is no Contempt of any Court, whatſoever not to ſubmit to its Decrees in a matter of Right, if any Party think himſelf ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43079:12"/> or if there be any legal Remedy, or any further Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal; for even the King frequently ſuffers himſelf in ſuch Matters to be caſt and over-ruled in his own Courts of Juſtice, and the Subject may try a Matter of Right with the Prince, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diminution to his Majeſty and Greatneſs, and without ſo much as incurring the leaſt Tittle of Diſpleaſure: for the King who is the great Fountain of Juſtice, as well as Honour, is always ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to deſire that Right may be done, though it be againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who is and ought to be content with the Enjoyment of his own juſt Regalities, Prerogatives and Rights, without invading the Property of his Subjects, which by his Truſt and Character he is obliged to protect; and the Caſe though in a leſſer Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the ſame, in every ſubordinate Magiſtrate whatſoever, who are what they are for this Intent and Purpoſe, that Right may be done in their reſpective Spheres, and that the Peace of the whole may be preſerved by the honorable, juſt, and candid Adminiſtration of all the ſeveral Parts, of which it conſiſts; and they ought to be ſo far from taking it ill, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders or Determinations are at any time diſputed, by a fair Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, or by an higher Appeal, that it concerns them in point of Juſtice to favour it, and to review impartially and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly what they have done; unleſs it be in ſuch Caſes where the Repreſentation is manifeſtly litigious, without any colour of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to ſupport it, which when it is ſo, it is eaſie to diſcern: but if there be a ſpecious Pretence, and the Law allows a farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry and reſearch into the matter, though perhaps at the long run it will not be able to juſtifie it ſelf; in this Caſe it is for the Honour and Vindication of Juſtice, that the whole Cauſe ſhould be brought under a new Examination; and for this Reaſon it is that our Law ſuffers ſo many Suits to be commenced, that in their Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have a quarrelſome and vexatious Face, a litigious appearance, and a frivolous or a falſe Pretence, and in their iſſue prove to be no better, becauſe it is ſo very tender of denying Juſtice to any, and therefore in purſuance of this its great Deſign, it muſt ſubmit to many troubleſom and impertinent things, to prevent the leaſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard or ſhadow of doing wrong, though it always takes care by what is paſt, to prevent the like vexations to it ſelf and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for the Future, by bringing thoſe Perſons to Puniſhment, or branding them with Shame; and by that means diſabling them from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43079:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the like Practices and Deſigns in time to come, who are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of ſuch Miſchief and Inquietude to their Neighbours, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting Strife and Variance among them, or by ſeeking cauſes of Action and Complaint upon every ſlight or elſe upon no occaſion or upon falſe or frivolous Accuſations. But my Caſe, my <hi>Lord,</hi> is ſtill more favourable than any of theſe things, for either Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> inſiſts upon his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reall or pretended Right, which he ſaith returns again with the Reſtitution of the <hi>Charter;</hi> or elſe tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it for granted, that you may put in and put out whom you pleaſe, he depends upon your Order in the nature of a legal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, as I do upon that of the Commiſſioners, with the King's particular Knowledge and Conſent, granted in my behalf; and I am willing and ready at any time to bring either or both of theſe Points to a fair Tryal with him.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether he be reſtored upon the Reſtitution of the <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and in that Caſe he may claim without any Order of your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Court, and for ought I know, may ſue for and recover the mean Profits for theſe five years laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Whether the King's Order, which is in ſome ſort his Preſentation, or yours be Superiour, or whether your Order can cancel or evacuate his. I beſeeeh your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> to conſider and apply it favourably to my particular Caſe, that when two ſeveral Patrons have preſented to the ſame Living two ſeveral Clerks; it is never accounted any rudeneſs or indignity in either of them in the aſſerting of Right, which is much more ſacred than the Authority of any Perſon, and more inviolable than the reſpect that is due to him: I ſay, it is never accounted any affront or injury in this Caſe, for either of theſe Clerks to diſpute the Right and Title of that Patron by whom his Competitors Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are ſupported; and it is always left to the Clerks to fight it out at Law between themſelves, without any offence to the Patrons on either ſide, who muſt not take it ill that the Law hath its courſe, or that a Perſon who thinks himſelf injured ſeeks for Juſtice, as in bounden Duty to his own Welfare and Safety he is obliged to do, much leſs then, my <hi>Lord,</hi> have you and your worthy Brethren any Reaſon to take it ill, that I aſſert the King's Title and my own, which is founded upon it, in Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to yours, and that, I ſay, his legal Order cannot be rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by any Authority inferiour to it ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43079:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>If you leave Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> and me to the Law, as in fairneſs, I humbly conceive, you ought to do, this being an Argument that you pretend to no Power, but what in Juſtice you may, then I doubt not in the leaſt of an Event ſuitable to the manifeſt Honour and Equity of my Cauſe.</p>
            <p>If you apply to the King and Queen, you acknowledge by ſo doing, that the ordinary Methods of Law will not decide it to Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his advantage; and that your Orders are not found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Juſtice but only upon Will and Power, and yet when all is done, I humby hope their Majeſties will be graciouſly pleaſed to conſider in my Favour, that it is their Title I aſſert as well as my own; that very individual Power being now lodged in them, which was formerly in <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>James</hi> the Second, and that the legal Acts of thoſe two preceding Princes, cannot be rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without the Conſent of the Preſent, and ought not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcinded without a Reaſon, though they are the Judges whether there be Reaſon or no; and to their Royal Wiſdom and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I ſubmit it with all the Chearfulneſs and Reſignation that becomes me.</p>
            <p>I know their Sacred Majeſties will graciouſly conſider the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements they have been pleaſed ſo lately to condeſcend to, to maintain this poor <hi>Church of England,</hi> and to protect its <hi>Biſhops</hi> and its <hi>Clergy</hi> in all their juſt and legal Rights; and I have great Ground to hope and to believe, though I am not arrogantly to preſcribe to Princes; and cannot ſee ſo far as my Sovereign <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Lady,</hi> who are as the Angels of God, to diſcern betwixt Good and Evil, Juſt and Unjuſt, Right and Wrong, ſo far conſider my Title to this ſmall Pteferment, not worth the noiſe and duſt that hath been raiſed about it, as to aſſert and vindicate their own, and ſo far blend the Exerciſe of their Sovereign Power, with the more God-like Attributes of Wiſdom, Juſtice and Goodneſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which the Divinity it ſelf would be all thunderbolt, and his Omnipotence would be feared and hated, inſtead of being hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly worſhipped and adored; as to reflect a little, if ſo mean a care can find entertainment in a Royal Breaſt, upon the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Circumſtances betwixt my Antagoniſt and me, and let them decide the Controverſie between us.</p>
            <p>I rely upon the Royal Aſſurances they have given, not only the Church in general, but every individual Clergy-man belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43079:14"/> to it, with a Divine Faith, as knowing they are God's Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents, that have ſpoken it, whoſe word is as firm and as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable as the Pillars of Heaven from whence good Princes come, or the Foundations of the Earth committed to their Charge; <hi>the Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter of whoſe Kingdom is a right Scepter; and becauſe they have loved Righteouſneſs and hated Iniquity, therefore God, even their God, hath anointed them with the Oyl of Gladneſs above their fellows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To eject without Reaſon, out of a juſt and legal, though Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Poſſeſſion, with all profound Reverence and Duty be it ſpoken, is not that Protection, which their Majeſties have promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; which we their joyful and exultant Subjects expect, and which all that are not perfect Strangers to the Fame and Brightneſs of their Princely Virtues, <hi>whoſe Line is gone out through all the Earth, and their words to the end of the World,</hi> are ſatisfied and well aſſured they intend. The Globe of Majeſty put into their hands, was an Emblem of the firmneſs and ſtability of their Councels; and of that immoveable centre of Magnanimity and Juſtice, from whence all the Lines of Action and Adminiſtration are drawn, all equi-di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from their Sacred Head, and preſerving an inviolable Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Agreement, a fixt and unchangeable Proportion with each other; and the Scepter never moves to bruiſe, or to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, but as a ſign of Condeſcenſion, and a mark of Grace; and we are bleſs'd with Princes made by Heaven for Empire, that are not only as Auſpicious, and Fortunate as <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> but as Good and Virtuous, as <hi>Trajan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Majeſty did not onely declare at his firſt happy landing upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground, that the great and onely deſigns of that Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Expedition, were to aſſert the liberty of the Subject, and to vindicate the oppreſs'd, and every day more and more endangered Rights of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but of his continu'd reſolution to do both of theſe, he hath given us many freſh aſſurances, and to remove more effectually all ſort of doubt or ſcruple out of the minds of the moſt jealous and diſſatisfi'd Men, who becauſe they have been once deceived, are for ever after very difficult of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining belief, to the moſt ſolemn and ſerious aſſeverations that can be made, he hath bound himſelf and the illuſtrious Conſort of his Throne and Bed under the ſacred Obligation of an Oath, and the Parliament have unanimouſly addreſs'd and thanked him for theſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43079:14"/> his gracious purpoſes and reſolutions ſo ſolemnly made and ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently repeated; ſo that being legally put into this Place, being now in the actual Poſſeſſion of the ſame, and having no reaſon, that I know of, lying ſo hard upon me as to eject me from it, eſpecially for the ſake of Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> who hath no colour of a legal Claim, I have the Promiſe of their Majeſties Protection, and the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of that great Aſſembly with them, and I do as little doubt, upon a farther inſpection into this little Affair, when thoſe of greater moment will give you leave; but your Lordſhip and the Court of Aldermen will likewiſe think fit to confirm me in a Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion that hath ſome ſmall ſhare in the Parliaments Addreſs of thanks, and lays ſo juſt a Claim to the Aſſurances their Majeſties have given, and which in its root I take to be as legal, and almoſt as firm, as any other Poſſeſſion whatſoever.</p>
            <p>For though the tenure of a Man's Employment be onely <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> as mine indeed is with reſpect to a Power Superiour to yours, yet the general Law of Equity in all Poſſeſſions is, that all Perſons actually poſſeſs'd and capable of their reſpective Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and not miſdemeaning themſelves, ſhould continue in the Poſſeſſion they are in: for all Poſſeſſions by nature are <hi>primi occupantis,</hi> they belong to the firſt Poſſeſſor and to his Aſſigns af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him; all legal Poſſeſſions, as there is no juſt one in a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but what is ſo, if they are not limited to a certain time, are in reaſon inſeparable from the preſent actual Poſſeſſor, unleſs he ſhall voluntarily reſign it up, or ſhall incur ſome legal forfeiture or diſability, though the tenure be never ſo expreſly during pleaſure. It is true, a Maſter may turn away his Servant, as he pleaſeth; but if this Servant have behaved himſelf well, if the Maſter cannot ſerve himſelf better of another, and if beſides all this he have a deſire and ambition to continue in the Service, then there is an Obligation of ſome ſort of gratitude, as well as of the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal equity of all Poſſeſſions, not to deprive ſuch a Servant of his Employment for no Reaſon: acting without Reaſon being the firſt ſtep to Arbitrary Government in private or in publick Affairs, and the very next to acting againſt it; for he that acts without Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that is, without the impulſe and guidance of his Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, does manifeſtly yield too much to the blind and fantaſtick motions of his will, and this if we give it an Inch, will very ſoon take an Ell, it will act firſt without the leave o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Underſtanding
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43079:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Conſcience, and then in a direct oppoſition to them both, which is the heighth of Tyranny and Uſurpation, the root, ſtock and branch of Arbitrary Power, whoſe fruits are almoſt as fatal and deſtructive as thoſe of the forbidden Tree it ſelf, that bring us to the knowledg of Good by the want, of Evil by the deplorable expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of it, and intercept the way to Paradiſe with a Flaming Sword, branded by the Arm of a <hi>deſpotick Cherub</hi> to hinder us from coming any more at the Tree of Liberty and Life; not but that an Arbitrary dependence is what it is, and a Man may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedy be ejected out of it, though no reaſon be given, nor any ſhadow of a reaſon can be afforded; but then in this caſe the ſaying holds good, that <hi>ſummum jus eſt ſumma injuria,</hi> eſpecially if the Perſon thus diſplaced be deſtitute of any other equal or proportionable Subſiſtence, to that of which he is deprived, and hath not any Proviſion of the ſame, or near the ſame value to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelf unto, and much more when he that is ſubſtituted in his room can get little or nothing by ſupplanting the other, but only the gratification of an unchriſtian, uncharitable and inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſible Spleen; both of which are Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi>'s Caſe with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to me, ſo that my Ejection out of this Service, by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that hath ordained it, though it could be ſupported by the utmoſt Rigour of the Law, which I am well aſſured it can never be, yet would that Rigour be unjuſt, if not barbarous in it ſelf; and it would be an Offence, though not againſt the dry and dead letter of the Law, yet againſt that Soul and Life that gives the true Sanction and Authority to it; and that is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and the Equity upon which it proceeds; it would be an Offence againſt that univerſal Reaſon by which all and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Poſſeſſions are enſured; and that is founded in nothing elſe, but a juſt Poſſeſſion, without Injury or Oppreſſion to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a Performance of thoſe Conditions which are required re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively to the peaceable Enjoyment of this or that Advantage, and an equitable Conſent in the Over-ſeers of the Truſt, which is derived from both; for even a Freehold may be forfeited upon ſome Reaſons, and where there are no Reaſons moving to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but only Will and Pleaſure; there Will and Pleaſure ought not in Juſtice and Conſcience to take place, but even the moſt Arbitrary Dependence ought to be ſecure.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:43079:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The ſacred and ſtrict regard that is always had to an honeſt and juſt Poſſeſſion in the Law, is the Reaſon why a Tenant, tho without a Leaſe, cannot be ejected at pleaſure, and much leſs with it, by a concurrent Leaſe, to take place at the exſpiration of the term of the former, the ſaid Tenant paying and doing as by the Bargain and mutual Agreement he is obliged to do, and the ſame Reaſon holds in all manner of Rights, Poſſeſſions and Ejoyments, if in all Caſes it were equally attended to, as in ſtrict Juſtice and Conſcience it ought to be.</p>
            <p>But of all ſorts of Poſſeſſions, there are none more Sacred than thoſe that belong to the Function that is ſo, and ſo it hath been always taken from the higheſt and moſt remote Antiquity of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages, down to this very moment in which I am writing. By the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> there was a Proportion ſet apart out of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man's Offering, every Man's Eſtate, for the maintenance of the Prieſthood; which could not be alienated or converted to any other Uſe upon any pretence whatſoever; and this depended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Reaſon of Equity, which is certainly of Divine and Eternal Right, that they that attend upon the Altar ſhould alſo live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, and that the Thoughts of thoſe that miniſtred in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things belonging to the Sanctuary, ſhould not be perplexed and troubled with any Secular Cares, and by that means hindred in the awful, reverent and decent Performance of their Duty, which ought not and can never be performed, as it ſhould be, with a diſtracted Mind: the Reaſon of which holds ſtill more ſtrongly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel Diſpenſation, which is much more internal and thoughtful than the other, and differs as much as the Religion of a Philoſopher from that of a Mechanick, or the noble and refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Operations of the Mind, (all which the ſtudy of an uſeful and inſtructive Divinity will employ) from the groſs and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Services of the Body: It is a Religion which conſiſts not in ſo poor a thing as Sacrifice, which very little Manual Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may perform, but in Obedience, in Virtue, in Praiſe, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and Inſtruction, in the Exerciſe, Exaltation and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe beſt Faculties belonging to our Natures, by which we are Men, and by which we reſemble God, and by which alone we can be rendred capable of an happy Fruition and Enjoyment of him, of ſeeing and knowing him, not through a Glaſs, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in ſome competent meaſure, as he is in himſelf, full of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43079:16"/> his own Excellence, and diſcerned by his own Light, by tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing and tranſplanting into the habit of our Minds, the Image of thoſe Attributes and Perfections we adore.</p>
            <p>And in purſuance of the Reaſon of this Levitical Inſtitution, it was, That in all Chriſtian Nations, from an high and remote An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity to this time, there hath been a ſtanding and immoveable Proviſion for the Clergy, out of the Lands, Profits and Demeſns of Secular and Lay Perſons, by ſuch and ſuch ſtated Proportions, which may be demanded, ſued for, and recovered by Law as a Due; and which are ſettled upon the reſpective Incumbents for their Lives, if they do not of themſelves relinquiſh their ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, or are not guilty of ſuch ſcandalous and repeated Crimes, as to incur Suſpenſion <hi>à Beneficio,</hi> or abſolute Deprivation from the exerciſe of their Office, and from the Profits and Emoluments accruing by it; they are provided for with a preſent Subſiſtence, that they may not be diverted by the importunity of emergent Cares from a preſent actual Attendance upon their Duty, and this Subſiſtence of theirs was made perpetual, (and was much more competent in the ſmalleſt Livings in former Times than it is now) that ſo they might be rendered eaſie in their Minds, and void of an anxious Sollicitude for the future, which though not ſo great an impediment to the diſcharge of their Office, as preſent want and indigence muſt in Reaſon be, yet in ſome leſſer Proportion it will always be a Thorn of Vexation in their ſides; it will affect them more or leſs, according to the different Perſons they have to do with, and upon whom their dependence relies, it will have a great Influence upon ſome Tempers, beyond what it will have upon others; and laſtly it will be a means of an unreaſonable Subjection of the Clergy to the Laity, and the occaſion of many baſe Arts, and moſt unworthy Compliances with the Humours and Intereſts of unreaſonable People, whereby to reprieve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from an impending Ruine, and get ſome further momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, uncertain and deſpicable Reſpite in a ſlaviſh and arbitrary Dependence, fit for none but ſuch wretches as are capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing molded into all ſhapes, and of receiving all ſorts of ſervile and mean Impreſſions from ill Men, inſtead of being the happy Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Amendment and Reformation to them, by good ones of their own, made boldly and frankly without Fear or Favour,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43079:16"/> though not without a becoming Modeſty and Diſcretion, upon every fit and ſuitable Occaſion.</p>
            <p>Now the Reaſon upon which all thoſe Laws were made, is every whit as applicable to my own Caſe, though in outward form and appearance I hold by another Tenure, as it is to the reſt of my Brethren of the Clergy, who have a legal Freehold in what they enjoy; for Tithes were no otherwiſe of Divine Right, than as they were ordained by God upon an equitable and eternal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and are ſtill continued by Men upon the ſame, as to the ſubſtantial meaning of the Inſtitution, which was the ſupport and maintenance of the Clergy, or of that Order of Men, (as ſuch there ought to be in every Nation) that were dedicated and devoted to the Service of God, though as to the minute Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a Maintenance as that is, and as to the ways of Levying, Collecting or Diſtributing the ſame, it may admit of Change and Variation in different Times and Places. The Law of Tithes obligeth not ſo much by virtue of that Humane Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, no, nor of that Divine Authority neither, that firſt eſtabliſh'd it, either among the <hi>Jews</hi> or in any other Nation, for both of theſe Authorities, as ſacred as they are, and eſpecially the latter of them, yet ſeparate from Nature and eternal Reaſon, they are at beſt but poſitive and changeable things; but that which gives thoſe Laws, in the general conſidered, which are made for the ſupport and ſubſiſtence of the Clergy, an intrinſick and eſſential Character of Obligation, is the apparent Reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Equity and Juſtice of them, and that Equity appears as much in making the ſupport perpetual, as in giving it at all, becauſe the deſign of the one, for Reaſons that have been given, would be defeated and diſappointed without the other: and if this be equally the Caſe of all Eccleſiaſtical Preferments whatſoever, where a Subſiſtence for a Clergy man is appointed in Conſideration of a Duty to be done; the Tenure by which I hold, though it be onely <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> will not evacuate the general Equity of the Caſe, but all Men that have a Reverence to the Laws, a due regard to Religion, and the Miniſters of it, or a due ſence of the great and fundamental Reaſons upon which Bodies Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and Societies are built, and by which equal Juſtice is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to all, will never do any thing deliberately, and of ſet purpoſe againſt the manifeſt Equity upon which thoſe Laws are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43079:17"/> built, whoſe Obligation they will and ought always to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be valid and binding upon them, even where the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Letter doth not oblige.</p>
            <p>If a Man keep a Chaplain in his Houſe, as his Domeſtick, he may diſcard him when he pleaſeth for no Reaſon at all, unleſs it be that of retrenching his Expences, becauſe the Law doth not oblige him to retain ſuch a Perſon in his Houſe, but yet it muſt be confeſſed to be very hard, and by Conſequence next kin to unjuſt, to turn a Man of that Character out of doors, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other competent Proviſion, after he had deſerved well of the Family and his Patron for ſeveral years together; but where the Publick hath allowed a Maintenance out of the publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, there the Caſe and the Equity ariſing from it, is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as ſtrong and as clearly indiſpenſible in one Eccleſiaſtical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion as in another: all which if your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> will pleaſe candidly and impartially to apply to Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and mine, that he was legally ejected for many and great Cauſes, and that I was legally ſubſtituted in his Place, that he can get nothing by his Reſtitution, and that he hath as little Right to it, as he can get profit or advantage by it, and that I muſt only be a great and unreaſonable Looſer, with little or no profit accruing and redounding to him, beſides many other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which, I hope, your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> will ſome time or other take the leiſure to conſider; I doubt not but you will recall the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, you have paſt, and think it more for the Reputation and Intereſt of your Court to diſcard Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> than to protect him any longer; but if this be the meaning of an Arbitrary De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence, (and ſuch I acknowledge mine in ſome ſence to be, though, by Reaſon of my Character and Function, it be the leaſt Arbitrary of any in this Houſe) that it is a dependence ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly and entirely holding of unaccountable Will and Pleaſure, that a Man may be ejected out of it for no reaſon and againſt a great many, and all by thoſe who are not the proper and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Judges, to whom the determination of his Cauſe belongs, I ſee not but a Tenure from the Wind and Weather, may be every whit as certain and as firm as this, and I perceive I was miſtaken when I valued it at a Years Purchaſe, when in reality it is not worth one day.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43079:17"/>
            <p>Suppoſe, my <hi>Lord,</hi> that the Living of St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s had not been united to the <hi>Hoſpital</hi> in my Perſon, would you then have ſtript me of this my only dependence for the ſake of ſo ſmall an advantage to Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> as it is ſo plainly demonſtrable this will amount to? And yet if in ſtrict Juſtice you had been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to do it, you would have been equally obliged in that Caſe, as you are in this; but if you are not obliged in ſtrict Juſtice to deal with me after this manner, then, I hope, you will reflect upon the Reaſons of Equity which I have offered on my behalf; and upon the many Arguments that ſtrike with ſo much force, and unanimity againſt his Pretenſions, and ſhew ſo plainly beyond all Exception, that there is nothing but Injuſtice and Malice on his part, nothing but Fairneſs and Honeſty on mine.</p>
            <p>Beſides, that he cannot be reſident upon both Places at once; if he ſupplies this Place by a Curate, as I am juſt now inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he is about to do, and I know the Perſon who it is, <note n="*" place="margin">One that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attend the <hi>Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> at any time but on <hi>Sunday.</hi>
               </note> that I hope you will not, and I am very ſure in ſo inconſiderable a Preferment, but yet requiring ſo great and conſtant attendance as this does, you ought not to allow; Siſters and Cooks, and But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers Helpers have been heard of in this Houſe, but the <hi>Hoſpital<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> Helper, and that in his abſence too was never heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but if he reſides here, which I am morally certain he will never do, and puts a Curate into his other Place; this is directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Law againſt Pluralities, which will not permit a Man to be abſent and reſiant forty Miles from any of his Cures.</p>
            <p>Let us ſuppoſe again, my <hi>Lord,</hi> I beg your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> to excuſe the plainneſs of the Compariſon, that at the time when you were pleaſed to make an Order for me to reſign up my Place to Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> and as I have been inform'd, in caſe of Non-obedience to the ſaid Order on my part, that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> ſhould have all paſt Arrears, and all growing Profits, becoming due for the future, that you had further ordained, that I ſhould deliver up my Books, and whatſoever elſe I had in my Poſſeſſion to him. Would it in this Caſe have been interpreted a Contempt to the Court of <hi>Aldermen,</hi> if I ſhould refuſe to do as that Order appointed? No certainly, but all Men would purge and vindicate me by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that your <hi>Lordſhip</hi>'s and the Courts Juriſdiction did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo far, and that it was no Contempt of a lawful Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not to obey an Order that was illegal and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceeded the juſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43079:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> bounds and meaſures of the Court, from whence it proceeded; ſo that to apply this matter to the purpoſe: I beſeech your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and the reſt of the worthy Gentlemen concerned, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der firſt ſeriouſly whether your Order be legal, and within the Juriſdiction to which you may juſtly pretend, before you accuſe me of a rude Contempt, or affronting Diſobedience to ſo great and honourable a Court, a thing which I will never be guilty of to any of my Superiours, to the beſt of my Underſtanding, ſo long as I live, and upon this one point, my <hi>Lord,</hi> the whole Controverſie turns, whether your ſaid Order, which I cannot help ſaying, is very far equitable; be ſo much as ſtrictly legal or no.</p>
            <p>And to all this it is ſtill further to be added, that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> having received his juſt doom of ejection from above, made his actual Reſignation before a general Court, and I at the ſame time was actually ſubſtituted in his Room and Place, and he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards made a Sale of the Furniture of his Chamber to me; which I accordingly paid him for: So that here were all the Signs and Indications of a voluntary Reſignation on his Part, who did not ſtand it out, as thinking himſelf injured, as I have done, and all the Formalities of a legal and orderly Poſſeſſion on mine, which Poſſeſſion I am ſtill deſirous to keep till I am legally ejected from it.</p>
            <p>Another thing which in point of Argument I ſhall inſiſt upon, ſhall be taken from an Act of Parliament 25. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. and enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>an Act for preventing Dangers, which may happen from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Recuſants,</hi> and in the Preface of the ſaid Act, the deſign of it is ſaid to be, for <hi>quieting the minds of his Majeſties good Subjects,</hi> by which Act it is ordained and enacted that all and every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Perſons, as well Peers as Commoners, that ſhall bear any Office or Offices Civil or Military, or ſhall receive any Pay, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, Fee or Wages, by reaſon of any Patent or Grant from his Majeſty; or ſhall have Command or place of Truſt, from or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Majeſty, or from any of his Majeſties Predeceſſors, or by his or their Authority, or by Authority derived from him or them, within the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. or ſhall be of the Houſhold, or in the Service or Employment of his Majeſty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould within a time limited, be obliged to take the Oaths of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance and Supremacy, and alſo to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, according to the uſage of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:43079:18"/> publickly on a Lords day, commonly called Sunday, immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after divine Service and Sermon, within a certain and prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time; and further at the making and taking of the Oaths a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, they ſhould likewiſe make and ſubſcribe a Declaration in Manner and Form, as by the ſaid Act is ordained, under the ſame Penalties and Forfeitures as are appointed by it; which ſaid Penalties and Forfeitures were two-fold.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that all and every the Perſon or Perſons aforeſaid, that do or ſhall neglect or refuſe to take the ſaid Oaths and Sacrament, in the ſaid Courts and Places, and at the reſpective times aforeſaid, ſhall be <hi>ipſo facto</hi> adjudged incapable, and diſabled in Law, to all Inrents and Purpoſes whatſoever, to have, occupy, or enjoy the ſaid Office or Offices, Employment or Employments, which ſhall be void, and are hereby adjudged void.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is further enacted, that all and every ſuch Perſon or Perſons that ſhall neglect or refuſe to take the ſaid Oaths, or the Sacrament as aforeſaid, within the Times and in the Places aforeſaid, and in the manner aforeſaid, and yet after ſuch Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and Refuſal ſhall exerciſe any of the ſaid Offices and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments after the ſaid times expired, wherein he or they ought to have taken the ſame; and being thereupon lawfully convicted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> every ſuch Perſon or Perſons ſhall be diſabled from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth to ſue or uſe any Action, Plaint, Bill or Information in Courſe of Law, or to proſecute any Writ, in any Court of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, or to be Guardian of any Child, or Executor, or Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator of any Perſon, or capable of any Legacy or deed of Gift, or to bear any Office within this Realm of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. and ſhall forfeit five hundred Pounds, to be recovered by him, or them that ſhall ſue for the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From which brief Summary of the aforeſaid Act of Parliament, I ſhall make theſe following Obſervations.</p>
            <p>Firſt that Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual Perſons, conſidered purely as ſuch, are exempted from the Obligations and Penalties of the ſame; and that for ſeveral Reaſons.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the Act mentions no other Employments, but only Civil and Military, and by conſequence the Eccleſiaſtical by not being taken Notice of, are excluded.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is a Maxim among Naturaliſts, <hi>Natura nihil fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit fruſtra;</hi> and ſo it is alſo in Reaſon, <hi>fruſtra fit per plura quod
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43079:19"/> fieri poteſt per pauciora:</hi> And for this cauſe it was not deſigned that this Act ſhould extend to Clergy-men, or Spiritual Perſons, as ſuch; becauſe they were ſufficiently ſecured to the Proteſtant Intereſt before; as far as Oaths or Declarations, or any other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Significations of an inward meaning could do it; for there is no Clergy-man, nay, no Graduate in either of the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but as often as he hath taken any Degree whatſoever, hath taken, as a neceſſary Adjunct and Appendix to it, the Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance; he is bound to recognize the Kings Supremacy, as well in ſacred as in civil Cauſes, by the expreſs Inſtitution of that Directory for Prayer before Sermon, which the Canon hath enjoyned, and it is thought that the Forms of bidding Prayer in the injunctions of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. and Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> were enjoyn'd for nothing more (and ſome ſay only for that, it ſeeming otherwiſe unneceſſary after the morning Service,) but only to extort this repeated Recognition of the King or Queens Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy in all Cauſes, as often as ever he either preached himſelf, or read an appointed Homily to the People. Furthermore, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beneficed Clergy-man is obliged by his Office and Duty, as he is ſuch; at leaſt thrice every year, beſides what private Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions there may be, in the Viſitation of the Sick, which he cannot refuſe, both to take and give the Sacrament, according to the uſage of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> He ſubſcribes to the 39 Articles where Tranſubſtantiation is expreſly condemned, and to the Homilies wherein the Charge of the moſt groſs Idolatry is pathetically and elaborately laid, in three excellent Diſcourſes to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the Office of Conſecration of the Elements of Bread and Wine, which he that Adminiſters muſt always recite, otherwiſe there can be no Conſecration of them, according to the uſage of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly called, <hi>Theſe thy Creatures of Bread and Wine,</hi> even after the ſaid Conſecration is over, for there is no Perception or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of or in them before that time, and yet theſe are the very words of the Conſecrating Prayer, at the end of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Service; <hi>Hear us, O merciful Father, we moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, and grant that we receiving theſe thy Creatures of Bread and Wine,</hi> &amp;c. Now we cannot receive the <hi>Creatures</hi> of Bread and Wine, if after the words of Conſecration pronounced by the Prieſt, they do not continue to be ſuch, as well as they were
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43079:19"/> before; and therefore this is a plain Declaration of the Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Prieſt, that the ſaid Elements do ſtill remain to be what they were, before the Office of Conſecration began, in Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Popiſh Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, as any thing can be imagined. So that, I think, it is plain from all this, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Spiritual Perſons as ſuch, are not mentioned in this Act, but that they were under ſuch very ſtrict Antecedent Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before it, that it was impoſſible for them to give any further Satisfaction, than by Law they were already obliged to do: and that only Civil or Military Officers, and thoſe receiving Wages, Fee or Salary from the King, or by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity derived from him, were intended, appears to me very plain by a Proviſo, which is the laſt Clauſe of this Act, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is provided, with all the particularity and Caution that can be imagined, that this Act or any thing therein contained, ſhall not extend to the Office of any High Conſtable, Petty-Conſtable, Tithing-man, Head borough, Over-ſeer of the Poor, Church-War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Surveyor of the High-Ways, or any like inferiour civil Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, (inferiour, becauſe not receiving Wages or Salary from the Publick and excepted out of this Act likewiſe for another Reaſon, becauſe the Government of Pariſhes being every where in Proteſtant hands; there was little or no danger of any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts creeping into any of the afore-mentioned Places of inferiour Truſt or to any Office of Forreſter, or Keeper of any Park, Chace, Warren or Game, or of Bayliff of any Mannor or Lands, or to any like private Offices, which are here called private, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not receiving Wages or Salary from the King; not but that the Clergy have taken and do ſtill generally take this Teſt, as well as other Men; but this I conceive to be a Proteſtant Work of Supererrogation, unleſs it be done for Example to the People, which I confeſs to be a Reaſon of Prudence, though it be none of Obligation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſecond Obſervation I ſhall make, ſhall be, that the <hi>Lemma</hi> or Title of this Act, being; <hi>An Act for preventing Dangers that may happen from Popiſh Recuſants;</hi> and the declared Intention of it in the Preface of the Act, being, <hi>For the quieting the Minds of his Majeſties good Subjects:</hi> It is certain, that it ought to be interpreted in particular Caſes, in all the reaſonable lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude that can be imagined; the Act it ſelf being made out of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43079:20"/> extreme caution, after many other antecedent Proviſions, that had been made againſt Popery in former times, and it being impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, as all good Proteſtants will very readily grant, to be too ſollicitous and careful, for preventing the dangers that may happen from Popiſh Recuſants, or as all good Patriots and good Men will ſay, to take too great Care for preſerving of the Peace, (which by Fears and Jealouſies is in danger of being diſturbed) and for the quieting the Minds of his Majeſties good Subjects.</p>
            <p>And how very careful the makers of this Act were, for the avoiding the dangers that were intended to be prevented and obviated by it, beſides the general Scope, and declared Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame, and beſides that this is but one Act amongſt, and after many that were then in force, to root out the Fears and Dangers of Popery from amongſt us, and to quaſh all attempts of introducing it any more, will further appear by theſe three Clauſes to be met with in it.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, <hi>p.</hi> 145, 146. a Clauſe concerning a married Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or Perſon under the Age of eighteen years or beyond or upon the Seas or found by the lawful Oaths of twelve Men to be <hi>non compos mentis,</hi> and it is provided with particularities needleſs to my purpoſe to be here recited, that no ſuch Perſon ſhall by virtue of this Act loſe or forfeit any ſuch his or her Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, (other than ſuch married Woman during the Life of her Husband only) for any neglect or refuſal of taking the Oaths, and doing the other things required by this Act to be done by Perſons having Offices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where (to omit Minors and Perſons that are not of a ſound Mind, who may have civil Offices by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; or by virtue of ſome grant before the time of their falling into Diſtraction) when even Women are here mentioned, and are obliged to take the Oaths, and do other things requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as appears immediately after, within four Months after the death of the Husband; this ſhews that civil Offices in the true intent and meaning of this Act, muſt needs be taken in a very large and comprehenſive Senſe, and that any Employment is a civil Office, if it be neither Military nor Eccleſiaſtical, which receives Salary and Wages from the King.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>p.</hi> 146, 147. of the ſaid Act there is another Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that nothing in that Act contained ſhall extend to make any forfeiture, diſability, or incapacity, in, by, or upon any Non-commiſſion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43079:20"/> Officer of Officers, in his Majeſties Navy, if ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer or Officers ſhall only ſubſcribe the Declaration therein re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, in manner as the ſame is directed.</p>
            <p>Now by this Clauſe, it appears, that the Maſter and his Mate in a King's Ship, who, I have been informed, are not Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Officers, and who are indeed in no other quality on board of a Man of War, than the ſame Perſons with the ſame Titles, would have been on board of a Merchant, are to take this Teſt, as to the ſubſtance and fundamental point thereof, which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, by a written Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or Subſcription under their reſpective Hands; and all this though they have no immediate Commiſſion from the King, and are not ſo much as Military Officers, only becauſe they receive a certain Salary or Wages from him; ſo that this is another ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plain indication in how great latitude the term of civil Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is in this Act of Parliament to be underſtood, as in the King's Houſhold every reſpective Domeſtick, though of never ſo infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior quality, and though in any other Family, being in the ſame Employments, they would be under no Obligation to take this Teſt by virtue of this Act, yet being of his Majeſties own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Family, (though a Porter, a Cook, a Butler, a Launderer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be Officers rather to be called Oeconomical than Civil) meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by virtue of their receiving Salary and Wages from the King, and being in an Employment of what nature ſoever under him, they ſhall be obliged to take the Oaths, and make the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in manner and form, as by that Act is preſcribed.</p>
            <p>The third thing I intended, to prove the great extent and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in which this Act is to be underſtood, is what hath been ſaid already of High-Conſtables, Tithing men, and other Officers of Pariſhes, or Hundreds, who are excepted out of it; firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no great danger of ſuch being Popiſh Recuſants, they being generally ſo well known to their Neighbours before their entrance into their reſpective Charges and Employments, and ſecondly, becauſe they do not act immediately by the King's Commiſſion, neither, thirdly and laſtly, do they receive any Fee, Salary or Wages from him; but then <hi>exceptio firmat regulam in non exceptis,</hi> in thoſe Places or Offices, that are not here excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in thoſe Offices where there may be danger from Popiſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants, acting by the King's Commiſſion, or by Authority deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43079:21"/> from him or his Predeceſſors, and receiving the King's Pay, or which is all one a Salary, Fee or Wages out of the Publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue; the Obligation of this Act is ſtill ſo much the ſtronger, and is ſuppoſed to extend the more indiſpenſably to them; and though in this Clauſe the Office of Forreſter, or Keeper of any Park, Chace, Warren, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be likewiſe excepted, yet this I conceive is to be underſtood only of the Parks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Nobility and Gentry, and that the Lord-warden of the Forreſts, or the Ranger of any of the King's Parks, receiving Wages or Perqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites from under the King, by virtue of their Places, ſhall not be exempted by virtue of this Clauſe, or any thing therein contained.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I humbly beg your Pardon, that I am thus tedious and importunate to your Lordſhip, but I muſt not be wanting to my neceſſary defence, and muſt rather chuſe, (though it be an hard neceſſity, and ſuch a <hi>dilemma</hi> as I could be very glad to have been freed from both its Parts,) to be rude and troubleſome to your Lordſhips Leiſure, which hath ſo many things of greater Conſequence to employ it ſelf about, than fail in the firſt and moſt eſſential Duty belonging to humane Life, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſelf-preſervation, ſo far and no farther, as that end may be compaſſed by Means that are good and lawful.</p>
            <p>Therefore as a third general Head of Obſervation, ariſing from the Act of Parliament above-mentioned, your Lordſhip may be pleaſed to take Notice, not only that to avoid any too nice Diſpute about what are Military, Civil, or Oeconomical Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, any Service or Employment of His Majeſty, receiving Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary and Wages from him (For that is always to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) is lyable and obnoxious to the Obligation and Penalty of this Law, <hi>p.</hi> 136. but that it is ſufficient as is declared in the Words immediately foregoing, if it be an Employment holding from any of his Majeſties Predeceſſors, or by his or their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or by Authority derived from him or them, within the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo having made theſe general Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, with your Lordſhips good Leave, I ſhall apply theſe Preliminaries to Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi>'s Caſe, and ſee how far he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in this Parliamentary Act, and in the Penalties and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures accruing by it, and redounding from it, in Caſe of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to what it enjoyns.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi>'s Office is manifeſtly an Office receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43079:21"/> Wages or Salary, by Virtue of a Grant or Patent from his Majeſties Royal Predeceſſor King <hi>Edward</hi> VI.</p>
            <p>Secondly, admitting that it was an Employment purely Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual or Eccleſiaſtical, yet Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> at his admiſſion into it, and for ſome years after, was no ſpiritual Perſon in any legal Conſtruction, ſo that receiving Wages from the King, for the diſcharge of an Office which could not be ſpiritual, unleſs the Perſon diſcharging it had been ſo, he was obliged to give that Security, which this Act requires, that he was no popiſh Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and for default of ſo doing he was legally ejected, and was, and is ſtill obnoxious to all the Penalties and Forfeitures of the ſaid Act.</p>
            <p>His being at the ſame time a non-conforming Miniſter, bound the Obligation of taking this Paliamentary Teſt, ſtill the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably upon him, for they are many times (without diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to any honeſt Man of any diſſenting Perſuaſion) Wolves in Sheeps Clothing, the very firſt beginnings of Separation and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> were from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as your Lordſhip may be ſatisfi'd, by the Peruſal of a little but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſeful Book, entituled <hi>Foxes and Firebrands,</hi> wherein this is made out by undeniable Matters of Fact, that will not bear any Shadow of Diſpute.</p>
            <p>The Congregation <hi>de propagandâ fide</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> have determined this to be the moſt effectual Way to reſtore the pretended Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Religion, to ſow Diviſions and Animoſities among thoſe that have ſeparated from it, and have forſaken that Superſtitious and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous Communion, and the late Project of an univerſal Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration endeavoured firſt by <hi>Coleman,</hi> as appears by his Letters that were produced at his Tryal, and owned by himſelf, and ſince pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and afterwards put in practice by others of the ſame Party, for the ſame reaſons, is a ſenſible demonſtration, of which we are all Witneſſes, that in the Judgment of the Papiſts themſelves, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion in general is highly endangered, by the diſagreements of Proteſtants among themſelves, and that not only by thoſe Feuds and Animoſities, which do but too naturally ariſe from a religious diſſent, through the heat and zeal of the contending Parties, but alſo by the ſecret practices of Seminaries and Popiſh Prieſts, who appear in all ſhapes, and have their Incendiaries every where to blow up every coal, whereſoever they ſee any thing of combuſtible Matter
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43079:22"/> that hath but never ſo faint a poſſibility of being improved into an actual Flame.</p>
            <p>I do not ſay, neither do I indeed believe it, that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> is a Papiſt or ſo much as Popiſhly affected, though ſuch Tools as he may drive on Popiſh Deſigns without ſo much as knowing that they do ſo. But this I ſay, my <hi>Lord,</hi> that this Act being made expreſly, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many other Proviſions of a like nature, for the preventing of dangers that may happen from Popiſh Recuſants, and for the quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Minds of his Majeſties good Subjects, and the only Reaſon why Clergy men, or Eccleſiaſticks, or Spiritual Perſons in the legal ſenſe are not, as ſuch, obliged by this Act to give the ſecurity requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by it, in manner and form as is preſcribed, being that they were beforehand with the Act it ſelf, and were all of them under very ſtrong antecedent Obligations, to give undoubted ſatisfaction, ſo far as Oaths and Subſcriptions can oblige Men, of their firm adherence to the Proteſtant Religion and Intereſt. It follows unavoidably, that Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> who received a Salary from the King for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of a Truſt, having never given that ſecurity which the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment required from all that were ſo truſted, and ſo paid, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beſides a ſuſpicious Perſon, upon account of his diſſent, there ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſeveral ſuch that were Prieſts and Seminaries of the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> I ſay, it follows inevitably that he muſt needs come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reach of this Act, for the preventing of dangers that may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen from Popiſh Recuſants, and for the quieting the minds of his Majeſties Good Subjects, and that for not doing as that Act requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he hath incurred the forfeitures and diſabilities ariſing from the Breach and Violation of it.</p>
            <p>I take it, that all the Officers belonging to this Houſe, receiving Wages or Salary by virtue of a Grant or Patent from their Majeſties Royal Predeceſſor, and by Authority derived from it, were obliged to take this Teſt, and for not doing it, all Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Collegues, as well as himſelf, were legally incapacitated to hold their reſpective Employments; but this, for the Reaſons that have been mentioned, concerns Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> much more than it doth any other. For it is plain the makers of this Act thought there was no ſecurity, that might be rely'd upon, that a Man was no Popiſh Recuſant, but by doing, ſubſcribing, and ſwearing as that Act requires; and how dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous it muſt needs be to put, though but a ſuſpected or a poſſible Papiſt into ſuch a Poſt as his, where there are continually ſo many,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43079:22"/> not only ſick, but dying Perſons, I leave your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to determine: and I appeal to all the World, whether a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Papiſt might not every whit as legally have been choſen into this Houſe in Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Station, as Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> himſelf in a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Poſt, having the cure of the Souls of this <hi>Hoſpital</hi> committed to him, receiving Wages out of the publick Revenue for his Service, and not giving that ſecurity which the Act requires.</p>
            <p>Neither doth it ſignifie any thing in this caſe, that we are all <hi>hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Servants,</hi> as the printed Ordinances of St. <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew's Hoſpital</hi> do expreſly call us, and that we are all <note place="margin">Printed at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, 1652. p.</hi> 1.</note> of us dependent upon pleaſure, (notwithſtanding as I have ſaid, we may lay claim to an equitable Right) for juſt ſo are moſt of the Officers of the King's Houſhold, as alſo of the Cuſtoms and Exciſe; and yet they ſhall be and they are all of them in common practice, obliged to take this Teſt by virtue of this Act, meerly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of their receiving Wages and Salary from the King, let their Places be never ſo arbitrary and dependent; and in caſe of Competition, for Example, betwixt Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> and me, the one to be continued in his Poſſeſſion, the other to be reſtored, I ſuppoſe theſe three things will be granted, firſt, that he that was legally ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted into his Poſſeſſion, being of that Communion, that Order of Men, of which he ought by Law to be, is preferrable to him that was not, in point of right, though the tenure be only <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> becauſe that <hi>beneplacitum</hi> can never extend to any thing repugnant to or inconſiſtent with the Law.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That he that after Election did within the time limited qualifie himſelf, by doing thoſe things required by this Act, for the peaceable Enjoyment of his Place, hath alſo another Title which the other wants, ſo that he is in two reſpects preferrable before him, and ought to be conſidered without regard to the other, by all that will make the Law the meaſure and rule of their Actions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It is no leſs plain from the words of the Act it ſelf, that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> having formerly incurred a diſability, though he have poſſibly ſince taken this Parliamentary-Teſt, yet he cannot be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his Place again in prejudice to any that was ſubſtituted in his room, and had an antecedent Qualification for the Place by virtue of his being actually in <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> according to Law, and a Subſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, by doing within the time limited, as this Act required; for theſe are the very expreſs words of the Act it ſelf, and, I hope, your
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43079:23"/> 
               <hi>Lordſhip</hi> and the Court of <hi>Aldermen</hi> will not think it fit or reaſonable to diſpenſe with an Act of Parliament, an Act of ſuch Conſequence as this is, for the ſecurity of the Proteſtant Religion, at the very time when the Parliament is ſitting, and is conſidering even of further Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities to obviate the dangers ariſing from Popiſh Recuſants.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Provided alſo that any Perſon, who by his or her neglect or refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, according to this Act, ſhall loſe or forfeit any Office, <note place="margin">p. 146.</note> may be capable by a new Grant of the ſaid Office or of any other, and to have and hold the ſame again, ſuch perſon taking the ſaid Oaths, and doing all other things required by this Act, ſo as ſuch Office be not granted unto and actually enjoyed by ſome other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, at the time of the re-granting thereof:</q> Therefore either this Act is not good Law, which I know your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> as well out of piety and zeal to the Proteſtant Religion, as for other Reaſons will be very far from allowing, or Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> cannot be reſtored, by any thing leſs than an Act of Parliament made in his behalf, in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to me.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing which I ſhall mention to prove that the <hi>Hoſpital<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi>'s place, though Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> had been in Orders as he was not, comes within the Obligation of this Act, ſhall be taken from this Conſideration, that the place is of a mixt nature, and is not wholly Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtick; I ſhall lay down the full and entire De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it, as I find it in the printed Orders of St. <hi>Bartholomew's Hoſpital</hi> above cited, which are the ſame with ours, as to the nature of the reſpective places, and the Obligations depending on them, and then leave it to be conſidered, whether Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> in his Oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Capacity, whatever becomes of his Sacred, receiving Wages from the King, was not equally obliged to take the Teſt with a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in Office, whoſe Office can hardly be ſaid to be civil in any other, than a very large and comprehenſive ſence of that word, or with an hired Servant of the King's Houſhold, or an Officer of his Cuſtoms or Exciſe, or a Non-commiſſion Officer of a Ship, receiving Pay from the King or from thoſe that act by Authority derived from him.</p>
            <p>The words of that Book are as follows, <hi>p.</hi> 17.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Office of an Hoſpitaller.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>YOur Office is chiefly and moſt principally to viſit the poor in their Extremes and Sickneſſes, and to miniſter unto them the moſt wholeſome and neceſſary Doctrine of Gods comfortable Word, as well by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43079:23"/> reading and preaching, as alſo by miniſtring the Sacrament of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion at times convenient.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To receive alſo into this Houſe, of the Steward, to the uſe of the ſame poor, ſuch Victuals and other Proviſion as by him ſhall be provided, entring the ſame into your Book, and ſafely to keep them to their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alſo to deliver unto the Cook of this Houſe from time to time, ſo much of the ſame Victuals as ſhall be needful for the preſent time, to be dreſſed for the poor; and the ſame being dreſſed to ſee ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, and truly delivered, and diſtributed unto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alſo whenſoever any poor Perſon ſhall be here preſented or ſued for, to be admitted into this Houſe, you ſhall receive the ſame Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, calling unto you two of the Chirurgeons of this Houſe, to view and examin the Diſeaſe of the ſaid Perſon, whether it be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; if they Judge it curable then you by a Bill of your Hand to certifie the Name and Surname of the ſaid diſeaſed Perſon, unto the Almoners, or two of them at the leaſt, deſiring them to ſubſcribe their Names thereunto, and that being done, you to keep upon a file the ſame Bill for your VVarrant. And then ye ſhall commit the ſame poor to the Matron of this Houſe, to be placed accordingly as the Caſe ſhall require.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alſo at the Admiſſion of every poor Perſon into this Hoſpital, ye ſhall enquire what Mony or other Things of value, he or ſhe hath; and the ſame together with his or her Name to enter into your Book, and you to receive and ſafely keep the ſame, to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the ſame poor, to be delivered again unto him, her, or them, when they ſhall be cured out of this Houſe. And monthly to deliver to the ſaid Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners, a Copy of your Book of Entrances, that they may regiſter the ſame in the Book of their ordinary doings. And if ſuch poor fortune to deceaſe and dy in this Houſe, then you to deliver all ſuch Mony and other Things, as ſhall be in your Cuſtody, to the Treaſurer of this Houſe, for the time being, entring the ſame into your Book, to be committed and diſpoſed, to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the poor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And as often as any of the poor ſhall be cured and made whole, you with the Chirurgeons to preſent them to the Almoners of this Houſe, at their next Aſſembly here, and to regiſter in your Book their Names and Surnames of them, and every of them, with the Day and Year of their delivery and departure out of this Houſe. And at their departure to give them a Paſs-port, to be made accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Precedent and Form that is expreſſed in the End of this Book,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:43079:24"/>
            <p>It is true indeed, that all the burthen, beſides what is Spiritual, is now by Cuſtom taken off of the <hi>Hoſpitallers</hi> ſhoulders, but yet ſtill the original Charge deriving from the ſacred and indiſpenſible Will of the Founder is the ſame; and he is to ſee, that they that in many of theſe things are but Subſtitutes acting under him, though appointed by the Governors, or by the King thereto, be not wanting in the diſcharge of the Truſt committed to them; and this implies likewiſe, that he ſhould be reſident, which Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> never was, and conſequently could not ſee to the Management of the Houſe; it implies likewiſe, that he ought not to be allowed to ſupply this place by a Curate, as he intends to do, becauſe he cannot tranſfer the authority committed to him, neither can the Curate by virtue of any ſuch delegated Power, correct or ſet right the abuſes, if any ſuch ſhall happen, of the Steward or other Officers, who are more or leſs under his Charge; and indeed if there were nothing, but the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual concern to be conſidered, yet it is ſo great a Truſt of that kind, where there are ſo many ſick, and ſo many wicked People, that it is eaſie to be diſcerned, that his actual reſidence at or near the Place, can never be excuſed or diſpenſed with upon any pretence whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, unleſs it be ſuch as our Statutes of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s College in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> call <hi>gravis aegrotatio,</hi> or <hi>violenta detentio,</hi> a conſtraint laid upon him by ſickneſs or by force. It was the Will of the Founder, that it ſhould be a Civil or Oeconomical Office, as well as a Spiritual; and therefore it is ſo ſtill, and he is paid his Wages upon both of theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, notwithſtanding the ordinary and immediate care of ſome things be by cuſtom and length of time, devolved upon others, that he may be the more at leiſure to attend to his Spiritual Charge.</p>
            <p>I have ſtill further to add, as to the buſineſs of Pluralities, that the Law makes a Living of eight pounds a year value in the K. Books; and Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi>'s is thirteen, to be ſuch a Living, as another cannot be held together with it, but within the diſtance, and with the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications required, and the Canon Law, which ſo far as it is conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to natural Reaſon and Juſtice is of eternal Obligation, is ſo ſtrict that even a ſmaller Living than this cannot and may not be held to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with another, and by this Law ſince the Reformation, <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Dean</hi> of <hi>Wells</hi> was deprived of his Deanery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had accepted a Prebend in the ſame Church <note place="margin">Dyer, 273. p. 35. cit. P. C. p. 19.</note> though neither of theſe Preferments were with Cure of Souls, and yet at the ſame time the Law is ſo favourable to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43079:24"/> Churches, that it hath been adjudged that two Rectories un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one roof, are no plurality, becauſe they are not in <hi>pluribus Ec<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 31. ib. cleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is,</hi> in more Churches than one; I have further to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that at the ſame time that I was put into this Place, my Father, as your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> well knows, was ejected out of another, which tho mean in it ſelf, was yet of a greater value than the advantage Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> can make, by holding this <hi>Hoſpital</hi> and his Living together; ſo that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> having no legal injury done him, as I have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently proved, and there being ſo many other equitable Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, beſides legal Pretentions on my ſide; I hope your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> will add to all this the loſs which my Father, your fellow Citizen ſuſtained, and will ſuffer that to intercede with you in behalf of his Son.</p>
            <p>And ſo I humbly beg your <hi>Lordſhip</hi>'s Pardon, for this long but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary trouble, wiſhing you with all my heart an happy Year, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous Government, a good old Age, and an eternal Youth in the Kingdom of the bleſſed, where there are Joys and Pleaſures at the Right hand of God for ever-more; and I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>
                  <hi>My</hi> Lord, </salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your</hi> Lordſhip'<hi>s moſt Humble and moſt Faithful Servant,</hi> John Turner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>To Mr.</hi> HUGHES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YOU ſee I have been at no ſmall pains to aſſert the Juſtice of my Cauſe againſt you. It is now your part, if you have any thing to ſay for your ſelf to produce it as publickly as I have done, that ſo the World and the Reaſon of Mankind may be the Judge of the Controverſie between us. I leave you to conſider what indifferent Perſons will ſay of you, eſpecially in your Circumſtances, who either are or ought to be an Example of Truth and Juſtice, if you ſtill perſiſt in ſnatching and extorting that by Power and Force, whoſe juſt Poſſeſſion you cannot ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly vindicate or defend, nor ſhew one Reaſon either from Law or Conſcience, why I ſhould be obliged to make a ſurrender to you. I do not deſpair, but the Reaſon and Equity of my Cauſe will be too hard for the real or pretended Inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt of yours; and I have here encloſed ſent you the true Copy of a Teſtimonial, which that learned and good Society, where I had my Education, were ſo kind to ſend me, hoping that their knowledge of that little merit, which they are pleaſed to ſay they diſcerned in me, might be of ſome Service to me in this preſent juncture, to ſhield me from the Violence and Injuſtice of your Perſecution againſt me. I doubt not, but I may obtain the ſame Honor and Obligation from the Profeſſors and Heads of Houſes in that Univerſity, if I deſire it; in the mean time take this, which I have ſet down without the names, becauſe I hope you will believe me, when it is ſo eaſie to convince me of a falſhood,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43079:25"/> if I have impoſed upon you or any body elſe, and becauſe theſe names ſhall be ſeen, God willing, together with others, if you have a mind to come to a Poll of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Clergy, and of the beſt and learnedſt among them, whether in common ſenſe and juſtice, to which we ought all to ſubmit, the place of</hi> Hoſpitaller <hi>of St.</hi> Thomas Southwark, <hi>be either yours or mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>THeſe are to certifie whom it may concern, that we the Maſter and Fellows of</hi> Chriſt's College, <hi>to whom Mr.</hi> John Turner, <hi>Maſter of Arts, and late Fellow of this our College was very well known; do hereby certifie, that the ſaid Mr.</hi> Turner <hi>had juſtly that Reputation among us, of a Perſon of great Learning, Integrity and peaceableneſs of Temper, whilſt Fellow with us, that we could have heartily recommended him, as very capable and deſerving of Preferment in the Church.</hi> Chriſt College, May <hi>7th</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now if after all this I muſt be run down by number and by force, which I can by no means induce my ſelf to believe I ſhall, yet it is my comfort that I have not yielded, and it is my firm Reſolution, that I never will, whatever becomes of me or of my Fortunes in the World, the loſs of which I value much leſs, than I do the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt and well-fare of Mankind, which cannot be ſupported otherwiſe than by every honeſt Man's ſtanding up in the defence of Juſtice, in their reſpective Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as far as it is proper for them, and as far as without Sedition and Turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence they may. It was old</hi> Caeneus'<hi>s Caſe, an Hero of whom the</hi> Grecian Bards <hi>make Honorable mention, to be driven into the Earth, by the dry ſtrength of blows, as a Pile to ſupport the weight that was upon it, when he could not be conquered and knew not how to yield.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>I leave it to you to conſtrue if you can, and I am, Sir, your humble Servant, expecting your Anſwer,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Turner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>
               <hi>EA demum Victoria eſt, quando victi vincentibus accedunt, adducti rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus, puerſuaſi argumentis, non telis obruti, non vi compulſi, non durâ Fortunae ingruentis neceſſitate coacti: Vincit qui patitur, quando cauſa triumphat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. P. Q. L. &amp; univerſo nomini Anglorum, ſub duplici auſpicio paris Auguſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimi, quos Amor &amp; Imperium feliciter conjungunt, ſalutem, pacem, concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam, charitatem; quáque domi, quà foris proſperos eventus optat</hi> Johannes Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>indigena Londinenſis &amp; Noſocomii Regalis quod eſt ad</hi> D. Thomae, <hi>in ſuburbano Municipio trans Thameſin ad Auſtrum ſito, Regio Prerogativae &amp; Patronatus Jure, Hoſpitalarius.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43079:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
